<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Bellum medicinale or The papers writen [sic] in defence of Dr. Brown his publication of the new cure of fevers, and which was so much opposed by a club of physicians; viz. 1. A letter &amp;c. concerning Dr. Brown's vindicatory schedule, and the dialogue written by some physicians in Edinburgh in answer thereto. 2. A looking glass for the black bond [sic] of doctors, &amp;c. 3. A third letter in vindication of Dr. Brown. 4. An epilogue to the five papers past betwixt Dr. E. and Dr. O. concerning the use of vomiting and purging in fevers.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 192 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 69 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B01559</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">51784368</idno>
  <idno type="VID">174794</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2240909105</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing B1860A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R172711</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">51784368</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B01559)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 174794)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English Books, 1641-1700 ; 2698:8)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Bellum medicinale or The papers writen [sic] in defence of Dr. Brown his publication of the new cure of fevers, and which was so much opposed by a club of physicians; viz. 1. A letter &amp;c. concerning Dr. Brown's vindicatory schedule, and the dialogue written by some physicians in Edinburgh in answer thereto. 2. A looking glass for the black bond [sic] of doctors, &amp;c. 3. A third letter in vindication of Dr. Brown. 4. An epilogue to the five papers past betwixt Dr. E. and Dr. O. concerning the use of vomiting and purging in fevers.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[3], 16, 47, [1], 14, 40, p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[s.n.,]</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Edinburgh :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Printed An: Dom: MDCXCIX. [1699]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Looking-glass for the black-band of doctors, and Epilogue to the five papers, have special t.p. and separate pagination.</note>
                  <note>"A third letter" has separate pagination.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect: tight binding with some loss of text.</note>
                  <note>Errata: p. [1] at end of second numbered section.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in: National Library of Scotland.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="personal_name">Brown, Andrew, fl. 1687-1691.</term>
               <term type="personal_name">Sydenham, Thomas, 1624-1689. --  Methodus curandi febres, propriis observationibus superstructa.</term>
               <term type="personal_name">Oliphant, Charles, ca. 1665-1719.</term>
               <term type="personal_name">Eizat, Edward, --  Sir.</term>
               <term type="topical_term">Fever --  Treatment --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term type="topical_term">Vomiting --  Therapeutic use --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term type="topical_term">Medicine --  Great Britain --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06 </date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-12 </date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02 </date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-05 </date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-08 </date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-12 </date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-02 </date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-05 </date>
            <label>Alexis (Ali) Jakobson </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-05 </date>
            <label>Alexis (Ali) Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:174794:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:174794:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:174794:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:174794:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:174794:3"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:174794:3"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:174794:4"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:174794:4"/>
            <p>BELLUM MEDICINALE OR The Papers writen in Defence of Dr. <hi>BROWN</hi>
            </p>
            <p>His Publication of the New Cure of Fevers, And which was so much opposed by a Club of Physicians; <hi>Viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. A Letter <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Concerning Dr. <hi>Brown</hi>'s Vin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicatory Schedule, and the Dialogue written by some Physicians in <hi>Edinburgh</hi> in Answer thereto.</p>
            <p>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. <hi>A Looking Glass for the Black Bond of Doctors</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. A third Letter in Vindication of Dr. <hi>BROWN.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. <hi>An Epilogue to the five Papers past betwixt Dr.</hi> E. <hi>and Dr.</hi> O. <hi>concerning the use of Vomiting and Purging in Fevers.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>EDINBURGH <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rinted <hi>An: Dom:</hi> MDCXCIX.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:174794:5"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:174794:5"/>
            <head>A LETTER Written to a Friend in the COUNTREY CONCERNING Dr. BROUN's <hi>Vindicatory Schedvle;</hi> And the DIALOGUE Written by some of the Physicians in <hi>Edin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burgh,</hi> in Answer thereunto.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Dear PHILOMATHES,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>OR Answer to Yours, I find thereby that Dr. <hi>Broun's Vin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicatory Schedule,</hi> which I sent you, has had the very same effects upon you both, as to Grief and Pleasure, which it hath had upon many Persons here: For as it hath raised your grief by the Reflection that your Loss might have been prevented, if
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:174794:6"/>your dear Friends which have died of <hi>Fe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> had gotten this method used to them; so m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ny here, who have lately had their Frien<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> also taken away by <hi>Fevers,</hi> have their gri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> awakened by the like sorrowful Resentmen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> when they perceive so much can be said fro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <hi>Reason</hi> and <hi>Experience</hi> for this New Method <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> curing <hi>Fevers by Purging.</hi> And tho the ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Charge to inquire about the Efficacy of t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> Practice doth ly on the <hi>Ph<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>sicians</hi> themselv<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> Yet because the Reception of it, as they a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>prehend, might brand many of them w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Oversight or Negligence, in that they ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> not been the first Discoverers or Intertai<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ers of the same themselves; they are ther<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore very active for the most part, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> that by the foulest means to suppress it.</p>
            <p>The other kind of Sentiments of Pleasur<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> which ye shew that Book has raised in yo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> is also common to many here; for the <hi>Inq<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>sitive</hi> are not a little delighted to find a Co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cern so important handled so <hi>Ingeniously,</hi> a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> a Design so profitable prosecute so <hi>plausib<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> Tho the <hi>medical art</hi> be truely, if it conta<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> any thing of Certainty or Reality, hid <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> deep from the eyes of Men, that the Wor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> is much in doubt wither it be an <hi>Art o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Artifice</hi> only: Yet I find, as ye likeway observe, that the Author in his book h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> done prettily to prove it may be an <hi>Art.</hi> But beside from what I have observed of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:174794:6"/>efficiacy of this new practice of purging in Fe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>vers, far beyond any other Method for cure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them, I am really induced to beleeve it is not only an <hi>Art,</hi> but a most usefull and <hi>Comfortable</hi> One.</p>
            <p>Albeit there seems to be nothing in that Book of his, which being duely considered, can in the Judgement of the most rigid Cri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick, be constructed justly offensive to any Man; yet I find perhaps by reason it speaks of <hi>Physicians</hi> Faults, it has bred a great deal of Grudge among them here; but how rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sonably will appear if we consider, that the Author for the good of Mankind in ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral, for the advancement of Medicine in particular, endevouring most Candidly to illustrate &amp; introduce a notable Improve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in Medicine; it was requisite for him first, to shew not only the necssary Qualifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions making Physicians capable thereof, &amp; the necessary means leading thereto: But al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>so to clear the cantrary Vices: that as barrs &amp; Impediments, hinder the admission of that <hi>improvement,</hi> and even before he should dip on the matter it self; For all the reason in the <hi>World</hi> will nor prevail with Men under any <hi>indisposition,</hi> making them uncapable to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive Truth. And further, altho the Authors main design had been to tax their faults, it was not; How could <hi>Physicians</hi> be offended thereat? when there is no particular conde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scendance
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:174794:7"/>on Persons, nor any Body named: Since all Men hear their Faults daily thus taxed in the Pulpits, and by Moral Writers in their most commendable Books, and that without any resentment at all. And as even the most guilty ought not to be reasonablie offended, so any that are picqued must be only the guilty.</p>
            <p>Notwithstanding of all these considerations, in the judgement of all judicious Persons, ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly clearing the Authors innocence, that Book has so raised the humours of some <hi>Physicians,</hi> that they breath out nothing but spight and malice against him: Which horrible <hi>Svmptom</hi> in <hi>Them,</hi> I think may be resol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved as to its true Genuine and natural cause, very easily Thus.</p>
            <p>It's notour, for the most part, that all Revolutions and Reformations are attended with a great strugle and commotion; because such changes, like <hi>Earthquakes,</hi> often alter the course and Channels that the Profits, Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferments, and other Allurements of the World, used to flow in. The <hi>Deitie</hi> of the <hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>na</hi> of <hi>Ephesus</hi> being in hazard, made these that lived by making her <hi>Silver Shrines</hi> made to think upon such a Revolution: And so there being many <hi>Physicians</hi> deeply interest<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the standing of old methodes, or these commonly practised by them, as the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct of what they call their <hi>long experience,</hi>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:174794:7"/>upon which they are valued by themselves, and the <hi>ignorant World,</hi> if these Methods should be overturned by any New, tho bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Practice, it might go near to reduce them to the same <hi>Level</hi> of <hi>Reputation</hi> with <hi>younger Physicians:</hi> No wonder then the attempt to deliver them from these, and to introduce better, be attended with great difficulty. If cutting off the hand that offends ones self can scarce be chearfully done, with how much pain will the cutting off a hand, that served of so great use, be?</p>
            <p>There has moreover alwayes <hi>predomin'd</hi> such a spirit of envy and pride among <hi>Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sicians,</hi> that all improvements offered by any of them, are with the greatest indig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation rejected by the generality, whose crasie Reputations can no wayes endured to be touched with so unsavourable a pinch, as the worthy discoveries from any others, may be in hazard to give it, of which among others was the difficult receptions of the circulation of the Blood is a witness: And this certainly has made many such <hi>Discoveries,</hi> to the great detriment of Mankind in general, and of Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicine in particular, to be buried with the <hi>Descoverers:</hi> Because all any could gain by discovery would be the hatred of others. And many in this present age, who have adjudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed these of the former to the infernal Pitt, for concealing their <hi>Improvements,</hi> are not
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:174794:8"/>withstanding so unreasonable, that they cannot endure any Discoveries made by these contemporary with themselves. An<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> therefore I think this attempt of Dr. <hi>Broun'<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> to promote Dr. <hi>Sydenhams</hi> new Method the more commendable, because both <hi>Ra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> and <hi>Resolute.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is an usual and useful Stratagem of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> old Serpent, the constant Enemie of Man<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>kind, when he cannot any longer withstan<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the Splendor and Brightness of <hi>Truth</hi> an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <hi>Light;</hi> to raise <hi>Mist,</hi> and <hi>Dust,</hi> and to thro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <hi>dirt</hi> on the <hi>Advancers</hi> and <hi>Propagators;</hi> think<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ing by an attempt on their <hi>Fame,</hi> to wea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>en their designes: And by raising a Frey, gain the main Victory over <hi>Truth:</hi> As th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> malicious <hi>Papists</hi> did against several of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Reformers, but especially against <hi>Luthe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> when they framed a rediculous <hi>Diaglogue,</hi> b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>twixt <hi>him</hi> and the <hi>devil:</hi> And as was lik<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> wayes done lately by the malicious En<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mies of Dr <hi>Sherlock</hi> in a <hi>Dialogue</hi> betwixt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <hi>Satan</hi> and Mr. <hi>Sherlock.</hi> And so you seem be a very true Prophet, when you say ye e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pect no solid Answer to that Book of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <hi>Broun's:</hi> for his Adversaries designing treat him after the same manner, are hopes to give him such a diversion tow<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the resentment of Injuries offered him will marr his prosecution of the main Ca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> or to put such <hi>Blunders</hi> upon him, as m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:174794:8"/>blast his endeavours: But I hope all wise Men, easily perceiving these <hi>Ambushes,</hi> will escape them: And that also, he becoming so great a <hi>publick Ʋndertaker,</hi> will slight all perso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal injuries; And hold on in the straight way of <hi>Vertue</hi> towards his Mark; where the Devil dare not meet him, who only haunts the By-wayes of <hi>detraction, malice,</hi> and <hi>defamation!</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And indeed when all considering Men, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause of the great import of the Debate in hand, were expecting from the <hi>dissenting Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sicians,</hi> a solid answer why they would not comply with that Method, behold there is come forth, and I have sent you it, a most <hi>Rediculous</hi> and <hi>Scurrilous Pamphlet</hi> by way of dialogue (the most sham way of reasoning) in imitation of these done against <hi>Luther</hi> and <hi>Sharlock.</hi> Containing nothing but Cavels Lies, and personal Refectious against Dr. <hi>Broun,</hi> at such a time (I say) when it was expected by all the World, that these <hi>dissent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Physicians,</hi> having the opportunity; would acquit themselves like Men of Parts, Vertue, and Probity, by some Learned and Grave Answer, which might make his book blush to stand beside it; and by such an Answer as would evince that they are no such Men as are taxed in that book, whose Reputation is a <hi>surreptious</hi> and <hi>fraudulent Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quisition,</hi> the effect rather of <hi>Artifice</hi> and <hi>por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pular
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:174794:9"/>Error,</hi> than of true Merit and skill and so prove that they were no ways uncapable of real and solid Improvements; but above all by such an answer as mtght shew they could both render a rerson for what they do, &amp; fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> what they refuse in this very concerning Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject as a good <hi>Christian</hi> of his Faith to the Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cusers: But how much wiser they have pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven then Mirry <hi>Andrews</hi> in that Dialogue, let all the World judge?</p>
            <p>Moreover the impudence of these Mer<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> in that <hi>Pamphet</hi> (beside the many other Fol<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lies they may be justly charged with) is ve<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ry strange, for how can they be so far de<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>luded as to think, in such an inquisitive &amp; preying age as this especially, while that book has had no smal reception amongst the judici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, considering also how unsuccessful the la<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> practice in <hi>Fevers</hi> has been, which has indeed put all Men under strange Jealousies thereof that any considering Man in such a weight<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> matter as this, will be put out off with <hi>Ban<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> Baufonrie:</hi> and meer <hi>Calumny;</hi> that Lybel of theirs, intituled <hi>A Survey</hi> containing no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thiog else, Tho the <hi>pe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ulancy</hi> of some <hi>super<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cial Pates</hi> like the Authors may be tickled and <hi>Palats</hi> tinged with the same <hi>virulence</hi> o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <hi>Malice</hi> with the <hi>Lybellers</hi> may be gratified with such <hi>Scurilities:</hi> yet all the wise and so<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ber people will look upon such <hi>Trash;</hi> as the most disgracefull peice of <hi>Rallerie</hi> could have
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:174794:9"/>been <hi>batched;</hi> and as unacceptable to Any, but such as are pitifully crackt, both in their <hi>Intellectuals</hi> and <hi>Morals.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Since then malicious Men are so vehe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mently bent to discourage all vertuous At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempts, becomes it not all good men who have large and publick Souls, to be as zeal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous to maintain them? but especially that Dr. <hi>Broun's</hi> present and most common double designe, suffer not by any sinister and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>direct <hi>Methods,</hi> the <hi>malevolent</hi> take to bring it into Neglect or contempt.</p>
            <p>Not that I would have any Body to think, that the Author Dr. <hi>Broun,</hi> for any thing his Enemies can do, will be deterred from the just prosecution of what he so much rec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kons the publick Good; all such Attempts on him proving like <hi>snuffers</hi> to the Candle to make the <hi>Vertue</hi> shine more bright, and indeed, whosoever shall consider the two last leaves of the Preface to his Book, will be ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly convinced, that he has not been so impru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent as not to have fully counted the coast of his undertaking, for there he makes his reckoning as a <hi>Champion</hi> for the puclick Good, to encounter malice, cartel envy; and to defy Detraction and Defamation: and as I know few would do the like, so I think when his Opposers Consttution, and Temper has so clearly discovered it self) that the judi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious will really conclude, it's no <hi>delusion</hi> makes him so <hi>couragious.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="10" facs="tcp:174794:10"/>
            <p>I know likewayes, that he was never so fond of the birth of his Brain, as to trust it into the World till it passed the <hi>Censure</hi> and <hi>Approbation</hi> both of <hi>Physicians,</hi> and of the most <hi>Learned</hi> and <hi>Judicious</hi> of the Nation, and these persons of the highest Rank; But espe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially the approbation of the honourable and <hi>Learned</hi> Patron of that <hi>Book;</hi> the Viscunt of <hi>Stair,</hi> whose concernment therein required a more close and narrow consideration there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of. As also the Author was so little Dog<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matical in his sentiments, that in a prefatory Epistle, he subjects his Book to the conside<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of all <hi>Ingenious Physicians.</hi> But mark the return he has gotten: The Tree is surely known by its Fruit, and waspish nature must out.</p>
            <p>But what need I say more of that Book envy and malice have fastned their Teeth in it, therefore it must be good, the <hi>Cank<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Worm</hi> seases alway the fairest fruit, th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <hi>Blood Hound</hi> singles out the <hi>Fatest Deir,</hi> vertu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> is still haunted with detraction, <hi>Themistocle</hi> said, alas, being now 22 years of age, I see have done nothing worthy, for no body i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <hi>Athens</hi> Envies me. And <hi>Hermocrates</hi> the <hi>Tyr<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rant</hi> of <hi>Sicilly</hi> said in his last advice to his son be thou nowayes envious thy self, but d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> thou Noble things that others may envy thee.</p>
            <p>And so I can assure you there is nothing
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:174794:10"/>such a perswasive to all Serious and sober men of Dr. <hi>Broun's</hi> Candor and Vertue, and of his adversaries naughtiness, as to find that he is obnoxious to no attacque, but that to which all Vertuous Actions and persons are open unto: that is, cavil and calumny, and indeed to see after 7 Moneths Deliberation, <hi>parturiunt montes,</hi> &amp;c. Nothing come forth against him, but a pamphlet stuffed with follies, impudent and bare faced malice. And for the witt of it, every <hi>Montebanks</hi> fool has all these stories, and ten times better on the stage every day: And it was undoubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edly from the consideration of the baseness of that pamphlet, that the Authors and — <hi>Mosman</hi> the Book binder, and Printer to the <hi>Assembly,</hi> (makes no Fool wiser,) Printer there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, have their names altogether supprest.</p>
            <p>Bot withal any man that will consider the success of the new practice of curing Fevers, by purg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing<note n="*" place="margin">That above the half of the physici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans in <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinburgh</hi> are eoncern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in it.</note>, will surely think the inso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence of these men in that pamph<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>let is yet more strange: for there passes few days but in <hi>accidentalren counters.</hi> I meet with some that tell me, either themselves, or their near Relation have been cured of Fevers by that <hi>Method.</hi> Neither ever can <hi>I</hi> hear of any dies under it. And this in a short time will probablie be so plain that it will wholly silence that <hi>Impudence</hi>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:174794:11"/>which indeeed no reason can tame: An<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> all the Opposition Dr. <hi>Broun</hi> seems to m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> with, I am sure will only serve to make h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <hi>Victory</hi> more <hi>signal</hi> &amp; his <hi>Triumph</hi> more <hi>glorious.</hi> As <hi>I</hi> could never meet with any that fro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Experience could condemn that Method, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> several that have tryed it, avow it to be th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> best ever they saw practised, and <hi>one affirmi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> Witness is better than ten denying:</hi> In this Ca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> as well as in any other, &amp; better then all the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> soplustuate and false waverings. And becau<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> I know it will not be unacceptable to you, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> have sent you so many of the persons Nam<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> and Cases (as I could easie remember) wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> have been thus cured to this purpose, that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> occasion offers, you may inquire at such <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> themselves as ye are acquainted with c;once<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ning the matter.</p>
            <p>The first I had from <hi>Commissar Scougal,</hi> wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> told me that he himself about 3 or 4 yea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> since, did take a <hi>Fever</hi> in <hi>Edinburgh,</hi> and bei<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> very apprehensive of the danger, because t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> last <hi>Fever</hi> he had several years before tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> brought him to the gates of death, So he w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> very doubtfull he could mantain such a bo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> again: and further being very diffident of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> old <hi>Methods</hi> by which he was treated in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> former <hi>Fever,</hi> and Judging this <hi>Method</hi> of pur<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ing to be more rational, he resolved to call f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> Dr. <hi>Broun,</hi> and not finding him in <hi>Edinburg<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> he sent to his house in the Countrey, an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:174794:11"/>brought him to <hi>Edinburgh,</hi> through which Method of Purging, in a short time, by the Blessing of GOD, the Commissar recovered.</p>
            <p>There is an other account I have from Mr. <hi>David Graham Tutor</hi> of <hi>Gorthy,</hi> and one of the <hi>Clarks</hi> to the <hi>Bills,</hi> who told me that within these 2. or 3. months, there was 4. or 5. per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ons dangerously sick of the <hi>Fever</hi> in his Fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y, his Neice a young Gentlewoman &amp; several of his Children, and a servant: his Gentleman missing Dr. <hi>Broun</hi> in <hi>Edinburgh,</hi> went himself in all haste to his house in the Countrey, ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nestly entreateing him to come to the help of his distressed Family: So <hi>Dr. Broun</hi> came a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ong with him, and in a short time, by the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>lessing of GOD, cured them all by the new method of purging.</p>
            <p>I met with a Minister here at the <hi>General Assembly,</hi> whose name is Mr. <hi>William Russell,</hi> I believe ye know him well enough, he gave me <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he following account; thus, In the beginning of this Winter, there raged in the parish of <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tobo</hi> where he is Minister, a most Edidemick and <hi>malignant Fever,</hi> few Families escaping, or <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ew in any Family but were affected, and many died, all the Ministers Family took it, and one died before he sent for Dr. <hi>Broun</hi> first <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o <hi>Edinburgh,</hi> where he missed him; thereaf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter he sent to his Countrey house, &amp; brought <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>im to his distressed Family, and in a short <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ime, by the Blessing of GOD, he cured him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:174794:12"/>his Wife who was given over by all, and several of his Children, by this <hi>Method of purging</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I have likewise the following account from <hi>Alexander Hamilton</hi> Bailie of <hi>Broxburn,</hi> who<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> Wife 2 or 3 years ago was most dangerousl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> sick of a <hi>Fever,</hi> so he sent for Dr. <hi>Broun</hi> to <hi>Edin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>burgh,</hi> where when he missed him, he sent t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> his house at <hi>Dolphingtoun</hi> &amp; brought him from thence to his Wife and by the blessing <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> God, she was cured by that method of purgin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> within a few dayes</p>
            <p>
               <hi>James Tod</hi> Stabler in the <hi>Grass-mercat</hi> told me that some 3. or 4: years agoe, he had a mo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> high &amp; raging <hi>Fever,</hi> so that he could scar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> be kept in Bed by these that waited on him &amp; having called for Dr. <hi>Brown</hi> the <hi>8th</hi> da<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> of his <hi>Fever</hi> after he was bled and purged, h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> peefectly came to his senses and calmed but had no memory of all that bad pasthin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> before, &amp; so by some more purging, and th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> rest of the <hi>Method</hi> he was perfectly Cured.</p>
            <p>The Lady <hi>Bagilo</hi> told me she had a daugh<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter, who some years before had a very grea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> and long <hi>Fever</hi> with a looseness all the tim<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> so that she very narrowly escaped at th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> time, and thereafter her daughter took th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <hi>Fever</hi> again, altogether after the same man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, and with a loosness also, after Dr. <hi>Brou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> was called, by the use of the new <hi>method</hi>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Purging, she was very perfectly and lo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> recovered.</p>
            <pb n="15" facs="tcp:174794:12"/>
            <p>It were long to tell you the particulars of many more I heard were cured this way of Purging by Dr. <hi>Broun,</hi> and others as <hi>Charles Divie Merchant, Archibald drummond Son to Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vost Drummond, a Child of Deacon Patersons, Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bert Clarksons writter, John Hunter Taylor, Mr. Alexander Mitchel, Chaplain to the Master of For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bes,</hi> a servant of Sir <hi>Robert Gordon</hi>'s, and se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral others; which any that is inquisitive may easily get notice of from the <hi>Apothecaries</hi> here especially, <hi>J: C: J: M: M.J: H:</hi> &amp; <hi>J: B: R: E:</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Whereas some ignorantly, others malici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ously, detract from the benefit of this <hi>method,</hi> alledging it is nowayes accommodate for all continual <hi>Fevers: I</hi> would ask such persons, if they can bring experience, to confirm what they say, and whether or not they deceive themselves, and others, with their capri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious reasonings; If they go about to overturn a matter founded on the solid experience of others: And if they be not as rediculous in such reasonings, as it would be horrible to see a man standing before the mouth of a Cannon, reasoning Gun-pouder out of its force, until he were all blown to peices.</p>
            <p>For it is very certain that Dr. <hi>Sydenham, Dr. Broun,</hi> and several others (who desire not to be named) have with the greatest success practised the purging method, this several years upon all <hi>Fevers</hi> that occurred to them,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:174794:13"/>even these with the most vehement <hi>Sympto<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> and that at all times and seasons of these <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers,</hi> providing the patients strength co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> bear it. <hi>Where it is to be remarked,</hi> that th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> is only mention'd what has been done; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> GOD only knows if this method or any <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther will alwayes hold, <hi>as also it is to be obs<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ed,</hi> that there is great Art and dexterly <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired in the using this <hi>method</hi> in difficult a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> dangerous caises, where it may miscarry the hands of Novices, or these unexperienc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> in it.</p>
            <p>And now to conclude all, I think the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious reflections on the whole matter, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> may give us a strange prospect of the nat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> of some men; so it admonisheth us <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> the greatest circumspection where we pl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> that important and exoberant Trust of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Health and Life. And so bids you Adu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your most hum<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> Servant <hi>PHILANDER</hi>
               </signed>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>Edinburgh</hi>
                  <date>15 <hi>January</hi> 1692</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="note">
            <p>Nota, <hi>These few instances here mentioned not to be lookt on, as all that can be given, t<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> being a great many more examples both in this <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> other places.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <head>ADVERTISEMENT;</head>
            <p>Dr. BROUNS Vindicatory Schedul<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <hi>sold at</hi> John Vallange's <hi>shop foregainst the C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <group>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:174794:14"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi>In speculo teipsum Contemplare Dr.</hi> BLACK.</p>
                  <p>A Looking-Glass for the Black-Band of <hi>Doctors.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>VVherein may be seen the Igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance and Malice of these <hi>Physicians,</hi> who have Clubbed under the Name of Dr. <hi>BLACK,</hi> for suppressing by their Scriblings, and other Calumnies, so great a benefite to the World, as the new Cure of Fevers.</p>
                  <p>Contained in a <hi>2d.</hi> Letter written by <hi>Philander</hi> to his Friend in the Countrey <hi>Philomathes.</hi> In Defence of <hi>Dr. BROƲN.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>EDINBƲRGH,</hi> Printed by the <hi>Heir</hi> of <hi>Andrew Anderson,</hi> Printer to their most Excellent Majesties, 1692.</p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:174794:15"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </div>
               <div type="precept">
                  <pb facs="tcp:174794:16"/>
                  <head>Dictum Biantis Prienensis.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>In speculo teipsum Contemplare, et si formosu apparebis, Age ea quae formam deceant, sin d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap> formis, quod in facie minus est, vel deest, id mor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>um pulchritudine pensato: Audito multa, loquere pauca.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>When every School-Boy knows this wise Pre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cept, <hi>Learned Club,</hi> you cannot be Ignoran<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> of it: But surely the Reason why you hav<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> so much slighted it, must be, because you hav<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> by the like Rapture of Learning, that you ex<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pounded <hi>Philander,</hi> (making thereof <hi>fool An<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dro</hi>) Taken <hi>Biantis</hi> for <hi>Banters,</hi> and <hi>Pirenens<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi> for <hi>pire-non-sense.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="to_the_reader">
                  <pb n="3" facs="tcp:174794:16"/>
                  <head>Advertisement by the Publisher <hi>TO The READER.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>ALbeit the Clubs Dialogue written against Dr. <hi>Brown,</hi> contained as much Impertinency, as might justly have moved any Man of moderat Mildness and Temper, to have Retorted it with the like. Yet Dr. <hi>Brown</hi> would so far <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>urmount these fools, who had no reason to be pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>vocked, that he would not be provocked tho he had rea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>son, and so there was in <hi>Philanders</hi> first Letter, a discreet, pertinent and solide Answer given them, wherein no man was touched. This Discretion, and Moderation, it seems, served then to no other use, than it doth to all Brutish, and Degenerous Spirits, to highten their Insolence, as ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared by A <hi>2d.</hi> Essay, emitted by them, a great deal more Infamous and Scurrilous, than the Former. Which, albeit it appeared very Rediculous to all Wise Men, yet in regard, a great many of the weaker sort of People, could not but be exceedingly amazed to see so many Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sicians, that pretend to no small Figure in their Professi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, Redicule an Improvement about the Cure of Fevers, made so Plausible by Dr. <hi>Brown</hi> and himself, Represented a meer Ignorant, and Impostor; this, as it proved very sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prizing, and astonishing, so it makes it very necessary, for satisfying the Curious, that there should be yet some Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>siderations offered, concerning the Buzle made about this very great Concern.</p>
                  <p>And <hi>First,</hi> It being plain, that although this Point of a most effectual Method of Curing Fevers, be of great Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:174794:17"/>to all Men, yet there are very few able by penetrat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing into the Mystery of the Debate, to be Competen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Judges thereof, the most part do therefore, by Implicit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Faith, acquiesce in the Authority of these, they thin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> should, and do know this matter thoroughly.</p>
                  <p>Yet as, <hi>Delirant reges, plectuntur achivi, So</hi> When Doctors rave</p>
                  <p>They fill the Grave.</p>
                  <p>For oftimes <hi>Physicians</hi> by their ascendant over the vul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar, having patcht up an Authority, calculat only for self Interest, they do thereby most Severely and Succes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully Tyrannize over Improvements, and their advancers<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> In regard they are jealous, such Improvements come to Supplant them, and steal away their Gods of Profit, and Esteem.</p>
                  <p>And next, since, in consequence of this, there seems to be no means left to Extricat this Improvement out of the Pounces of such <hi>Cormorants</hi> and <hi>Harpyes;</hi> but to represent them to the World, in their Natural and true Shape, and despoil them of their borrowed <hi>Plumes</hi> of un<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>merited <hi>Esteem,</hi> acquired through vulgar <hi>Ignorance,</hi> and <hi>Mistake.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>It seems absolutely necessary, for undeceiving the the World, and rescuing the true Interest of Mankind, to give Exact <hi>Characters</hi> of these <hi>Blacks, Wolfs</hi> in <hi>Sheeps Clothing,</hi> and <hi>Enemies to Men,</hi> at least in so far as their <hi>Scriblings</hi> and <hi>Calumnies</hi> declare them.</p>
                  <p>And so there being only here represented a true Histo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of Dr. <hi>Black's Phenomena,</hi> and these plainly solved, by laying down a solid <hi>Hypothesis</hi> of his <hi>Nature:</hi> I hope the <hi>Candid Reader</hi> will not Construct, that Dr. <hi>Broun</hi> is provocked, or that he intends Reviling for <hi>Reviling:</hi> but only that he designs, for the Publick Good, to give
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:174794:17"/>a true Representation of the weak Foundation of that <hi>Tyrannical Authority,</hi> which in its being is Calculated, and Contrived, and in its use is most advantageously ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ercised and imployed, for the Overthrow, and Suppres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion of so great Benefits, as Improvements in Medicine are; Their safety and progress being indeed no wayes at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainable, so long as men that can securely level at Self, and privat Interest, altho at the publick Coast, remain in Power and Credit with the World.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Philander</hi> has not gone to beg pitiful stories at the Common Strumpet <hi>Fame,</hi> to make up their History with, where perhaps he might have made als good pūrchase of Reproachful Tales, as <hi>Black</hi> has done, (none of the <hi>Black Club</hi> being either so Innocent in themselves, or such Darlings of Fame) for
<q>
                        <hi>Tam ficti pravi{que} tenax quam nuncia veri.</hi>
                     </q>
                  </p>
                  <p>But he has only made use of such <hi>Documents,</hi> as are drawn from their Writings, and other Actings about this Affair, and when no body is Named, if they hit not right, there is no miss made, and no body can Complain. And because <hi>Dr. Broun</hi> was unwilling to expose these Enemies of Truth, before he essayed all means for their Reformation, and endeavoured to beg Peace at their hands, long before they were Printed, he gave in his whole Papers to them, to be Considered, with the fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing Letter annexed thereto.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="statement">
                  <pb n="6" facs="tcp:174794:18"/>
                  <head>To all <hi>Physicians</hi> that are <hi>Dr. Broun's</hi> Enemies, or these who have Calumniat him by Printing against him, or otherwise, A Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritable Offer of Forgiveness and Peace.</head>
                  <p>THat <hi>Scurrilous</hi> Dialogue, Printed and Dispersed, with design to suppress my honest Endeavours in Relation to the Advancement of Medicine, and wherein you have been concerned, as <hi>Contrivers, Authors, Publish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers</hi> or <hi>Approvers,</hi> I studied a while to connive at, and to give it so General an Answer, as might not reflect par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularly on any of you, either directly, or by broa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> hints: Tho my Vindication in the Opinion of some, seem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in so far defective, that it stood meerly on the Defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sive, and not paying you home in the same Coyn, wante<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> some Trapings of <hi>Rallery,</hi> to have made it more <hi>Fashion<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able</hi> and <hi>Passing</hi> (that <hi>Rallery</hi> being always flat where <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> body is hit)</p>
                  <p>Untill your <hi>2d.</hi> Essay a great deal more Impertine<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> then the former, backed also with with your consta<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> verbal Calumnies, obliged me something to change th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> former Measures, and to give this Answer, which (<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> intending to be more Generous, than at a stollen Dint, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> make any of you Ridiculous,) I have sent you before <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> be Printed, to be perused: And if there be any thing them in you can evince Impertinent, either to my Vindcati<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> or the Vindication of the Improvement, I endeavour to advance, or a more severe <hi>Retaliation,</hi> th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="7" facs="tcp:174794:18"/>the Provocation Craved (your Scurilities and Calumnies indeed admitting of no other Answer.) I am content (as being willing to do my Enemies all Justice) it be in so far Reformed.</p>
                  <p>There was never any mans Reputation designed to be <hi>Impeached</hi> by me, unless in so far as it's Imployed to barr out Improvements; Some of your Reputations, I endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voured to advance <hi>pari passu</hi> with this Improvement; But If any m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ns backwardness, becoming too plain, derogat from that Portion of Reputation he is in possession of, he knows whom to blame for that. When Discoveries, and Mens Reputation turn <hi>Antipods,</hi> and <hi>opposite,</hi> the Discoveries tending to the <hi>Zenith,</hi> their Reputation will down to <hi>Nadir.</hi> And the greater Pouther be made about Discoveries, when they become Conspicuous, their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects will be the more Legible that make it: And as com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Prudence would oblige all that have common sence, rather hover a While, than precipitantly condemn mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of Experiment, which others have found, but they themselves have never seen; So indeed I think a very smal touch of the Conscience of your Duty, as <hi>Physicians,</hi> would make you carefully watch all opportunities to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serve whether or not this Practice hold to be as Succesful, as it is given forth, &amp; this (which is very strange,) none of you has ever yet taken the pains to do: And so how you can Answer, either for this neglect, or for your other behavior in this matter, to God or Man, I truly do not understand. If I have wronged any of you, I am content of just over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>urs for further satisfaction, than what already you have taken at your own hands, if further be due: And if you cannot make any wrong appear (which I think ye will not) I am content that being least in the Transgression, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> have the honour to be first in the desiring a Just Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commodation. It may be sufficiently known to you,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:174794:19"/>that I am several wayes (especially in regard of the cause) so advantageously stated, that <hi>I</hi> need not fear your attempt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> any other ways, then that they may hurt your selves and prejudge a while the advancement of Medicine. It's therefore Peace and Charity to you, and love to the Publick Good, moves me to this Advertisement.</p>
                  <p>Since then I am content on very easie terms to pass from any Retaliation, or exposing you, as here you see, as th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <hi>I</hi> conceive, will be a considerable evidence to the World, of my Peaceable and Charitable Disposition, so it will be a pregnant Testimony of my affection to the Art which by a Representation of the Matter, or a just Retaliation, may perhaps come to suffer: And show to all Men, that (like <hi>Solomons</hi> true Mother, that would by no means en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure the dividing of the living Child) that I am so ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of the Art, that I incline scarce at any rate to d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> ought that may tend to the exposing, or vilifying ther<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>of; and further, these Considerations (as I humbly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive) ought to invite you also to give the like Testimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of your peaceable Disposition, and of your like ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der affection to the <hi>Art,</hi> in reasonably preventing, what may any further marr the Honour or Advanc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> thereof.</p>
                  <p>If your return to this Letter, be any thing but Peace and Accommodation, you may expect the World will b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> acquainted with it in Print,</p>
                  <p>THe Clubs return to this, was in their old chat of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proaches, some of them, especially the <hi>Lame</hi> and th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <hi>Maimed</hi> answered it in a new <hi>Cant</hi> to the Tune of <hi>Cu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gelling,</hi> and <hi>Ear-cropping.</hi> O <hi>brave</hi> Doctors, who, having long since Banquerouted your Learning and Reason, to<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> first refuge in <hi>Banter</hi> and <hi>Ribauldrie,</hi> and now being bang<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> out of that, has no shelter left you, but to thuart nature so far, as to give your selves out for <hi>Hectors!</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="9" facs="tcp:174794:19"/>
                  <p>And so Candid Reader, I crave pardon for detaining you so long in prefacing to <hi>Philanders</hi> Letter, which will more fully give you the accompt of the whole mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and so bids you adieu.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>Your humble Servant, Philarchus.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div type="letter">
                  <head>ADVERTISEMENT.</head>
                  <p>LEarned and Witty <hi>Club,</hi> when I reflect, how Inge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuously you deciphered <hi>Philander,</hi> just as a <hi>Mounti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bank</hi>'s Fool would have done, taking it for <hi>Fool Andro.</hi> I would earnestly intreat, that ye do not Sore again so high, with an <hi>Icarian</hi> flight in Learning, and take this <hi>Philarchus</hi> for your Fool <hi>Arche,</hi> that meer <hi>Pageant</hi> of Learning, who being on of the Authors of that Learned <hi>Dialogue,</hi> written against Dr. <hi>Broun,</hi> thought to escape his Reward, because he was sheltered in a Chair; yet the <hi>Impudent Pretender Declaiming,</hi> or rather <hi>Belsching</hi> from the <hi>Chair</hi> his <hi>Foppry</hi> and <hi>Impertinency,</hi> has so well chas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tized himself, that no body needs to be further solicitous to take any other Correction of him, than by Publishing to the World his <hi>Inaugural Oration,</hi> with some <hi>Natural</hi> and <hi>Pertinent</hi> remarks thereupon; <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Unto which, if there be added, a full <hi>plan</hi> and <hi>History</hi> of the Means and Methods of his, most deserved Promo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; as thereby it will be clear, that the Air of our <hi>Climat</hi> is most apt to blow up <hi>Bubles,</hi> letting more solid things fall to the Bottom: So such a <hi>History</hi> as this will not be little delghtful to the <hi>Curious,</hi> to understand
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:174794:20"/>plainiy all these <hi>Petty Arts,</hi> and <hi>sham Tricks,</hi> by which this ape of Learning managed his <hi>Intrigue</hi> of <hi>applaus<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> Catching,</hi> and <hi>fame forstalling.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>If <hi>Hogen Mogen</hi> finding the pleasant Effects of this <hi>Pretty Art,</hi> complain that they are gulled, and that fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <hi>Juno</hi> they have embraced a cloud. I must crave <hi>Myn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heer</hi> pardon, if <hi>I</hi> tell him, that he must not think him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self abused, by these who gave the Man a brave recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendation, for the <hi>Scots Proverb,</hi> and <hi>Practise</hi> is, tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> these who are ill of their <hi>Harbour,</hi> a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e best of there a way Ken; and indeed the easiest way to be easily rid of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> troublesome <hi>Guest</hi> is always to <hi>ruse</hi> him.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="letter">
                  <head>A second Letter Written by <hi>Phil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ander,</hi> to his Freind in the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try <hi>Philomathes</hi> in Vindication of <hi>Dr. Brown.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>Dear <hi>Philomathes.</hi>
                     </salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>I Was not a little surprized as well as your self, when my former Letter written to you, and Published to the World, in Vindication of Dr. <hi>Broun</hi>'s Book, was An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swered by his Opposers, to whom it was not Directed: Ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>madversions, or Observations thereon, the <hi>Black</hi> Dr. might have Published, but his giving an Answer of a Letter not directed to him, seemed a nonsensical piece of business, I ruminated long to see if this Bull of the <hi>Black Drs.</hi> could be any way excused, at last I think I hit it, for <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing how Learnedly Dr. <hi>Black</hi> had deciphered <hi>Philanders,</hi>
                     <pb n="11" facs="tcp:174794:20"/>making it <hi>Fool Andro. I</hi> clearly understood, that the <hi>Black Dr.</hi> after the same manner, had deciphered your Name <hi>Philomathes,</hi> taking it for Fool <hi>Matthew</hi> one of their So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciety: this surely has made them rather Ignorantly, than altogether Impertinently Answer it, tho by as great a mistake, as if one should take <hi>Dr. Black</hi> for a <hi>Candid Dr.</hi> or <hi>White</hi> for <hi>Black,</hi> there being as great a difference be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt <hi>Phiomathes</hi> and <hi>Fool Matthew,</hi> so, as the <hi>Clinking</hi> of the Bell makes the Fool think, does, the gingling of Words make these wise <hi>Drs.</hi> rave. And now <hi>Philomathes,</hi> it were in vain to tell you how Infamously these <hi>Drs.</hi> in their Scurrillous Libels, bestow their Talent, and bewray their little Wit: every body that doth not, will fully shut his Eyes, must of necessity see every Line of these reproach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Stories against Dr. <hi>Brown,</hi> drawn in the black Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racters of Envy and Malice: and surely, because <hi>Dr. Brown</hi>'s Enemies could say little in the cause, and bring less a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst his Ingenuity, and Sincerity, they endeavour to mis-re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>present his extrinsick Qualifications, his Discretion, his Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour, or his Carriage, as if by making him Ridiculous in any of these, they can but abate Mens Reverence to him, their Confidence in him will not long hold out: For as one sayes bare honesty, being lookt on as a Leafless Tree, no body will trust himself to it's shelter: Thus <hi>Socrates</hi> was treated by his Enemies, when they could no other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways suppress his Reputation, they hired <hi>Aristophanes</hi> the <hi>comick</hi> Poet, to Personat him <hi>in redicule</hi> on the Stage.</p>
                  <p>And indeed I think no wonder these Gentlemen, for all their Impudence, had never Confidence enough to owne to the World what they had done against Dr. <hi>Broun.</hi> all Crimes have had their Fauters and Abettors, but Lying, especially reproachful Lying, is so much the Dregs and Refuse of Wickedness, that none has yet had Chimistry enough to Sublime it unto Reputation, so as any body will
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:174794:21"/>venter to owne it: and among the several Aggravations, this Crime is capable of (besides the cause a Man suffers reproach for) the putting of such reproachful lies in Print, seems none of the least: But let <hi>George Mosman</hi> look to thar.</p>
                  <p>I must confess, we are got into a very Merry World, if Men will be so foolish, as to suffer themselves at the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pence of their Health, the most valuable concern of Life, to be laught and lied too, out of so useful, and clear an Improvement to the Common Nature, as the Cure of Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers. Dr, <hi>Broun</hi> has in his Schedule, given an <hi>Idea</hi> of: <hi>I</hi> am willing to believe, there are a great many still, who have perspicacity enough to see thorow such sort of Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dresses, So that these Merchants will lye under a necessity to deal with the more Ignorant Chapmen, and with them their Counterfeit Wairs will go best off.</p>
                  <p>But pray let us take a sober view of what these Fopps, and Enemies to Mankind will be at: Here then, good <hi>Drs:</hi> Let us carefully weigh the matter, and lay in one <hi>Scale,</hi> the dearest concern under Heaven, the Health and Life of Men. and their nearest Relations, frequently overturned by these continual Fevers, the danger and precipitant Invasion thereof, which by a sudden Eruption and Devastation, in a trice overturn our Hopes and Comforts, to therefore make the loss of Life more bitter: and which is yet very recent with many, your former and present unsuccesful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness in the Cure of these Fevers.</p>
                  <p>And in the other <hi>Scale,</hi> let us lay the undoubted Obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation, chargeable on the <hi>Adepts,</hi> and Sons of Art, to Ransact and Muster all the Supplies, Study, Industry and Observation can make up for the Resistance of the sudden Ravage and Dissolution made by these Fevers: together with the great, constant and dayly Success, which to the great Comfort of Men, and their Relations, is observed to follow this new Method of Curing Fevers.</p>
                  <pb n="13" facs="tcp:174794:21"/>
                  <p>Now, my very good reverst Friends, to which of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>de does the <hi>Ballance</hi> incline to with you, and since you either close your Eyes from the wonderful Effects of this new Method, or dissemble, what you understand of it, are you not then in love with these many Ruins, and Distresses these Fevers bring along with them, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent to let your Blood freeze within you, in the midst of such extream heat, when upon every trivial occasion, at other times, it's ready to break out in the strangest Ebuli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: Is not this to prove your selves Fopps, your Art a Trick, and Induce the World to cry out, you can do no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, when there is most ado with you: <hi>Good Doctors,</hi> who appear to the vulgar sprightly Heroes in Medicine, I am al<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>most in a fright, when I consider with all, what a <hi>remora</hi> many such dead weights as you, really is in the way of true Practical Improvement in Medicine, to the great hurt of Mankind, and the scandal of all faithful <hi>Physicians,</hi> you are in truth, the dead Flees that Corrupt all their Perfums: For shameimust honest Dr. <hi>Broun</hi> meet with such dishonest treatment from you, for his Charitable Endeavours, to deliver the World from the fetters of Prejudice and Igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, &amp; wherein no Man is touched or wronged; it's not his own things he seeks, it's the Interest of Humanity, in so noble a Discovery of a new and most succesful method of Curing these formidable Fevers; So the malice must be strange and more than humane, that prosecuts him.</p>
                  <p>Since then <hi>Philom.</hi> as every body knows, this fearful havock of our Dearest Concerns made by these Fevers, of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten falls out, under the <hi>Presidence</hi> and <hi>Government</hi> of the <hi>Physicians,</hi> and seeing their Trust makes it nearly their concern, to enquire seriously, whether Negligence or Mistaks may be Concuring to the Course of so sudden and formi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dable a Devastation: and also, Seing we perceive Men are always with great difficulty, drawn from their former
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:174794:22"/>
                     <hi>Customs</hi> and <hi>Practices:</hi> and with all Ranks and Stations of Men, Improvements are hardly entertained and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>mbraced; but most of all, with those whose Esteem, and Reputati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on can be preserved intire without their entertaining them as in Medicine, I apprehend it's too easie to do.</p>
                  <p>Upon these Considerations <hi>Philomath,</hi> I am not only clearly Induced to entertain shrewd and harsh thoughts o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> those that are offended at the Preliminaries of <hi>Dr. Broun'<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi> Book; but I also think, he has made no Impertinent de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gression, but a very necessary Preliminary, and Preface to his Work, where he has made a <hi>Towr</hi> to Summond u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> the whole Force of that Obligation, lying on <hi>Phisicians</hi> to Dilligence and <hi>Improvement,</hi> to conjure down negli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence, and to areaign all vulgar Ertors and Mistakes ca<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pable to stiffle, or deprave Improvement in that Art, it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing indeed these that seem like Mountains, to stand it the way to Improvement; do they not then deserve by se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Consideration, to be Levelled and Removed.</p>
                  <p>Now <hi>Philom.</hi> Knowing you are a Curious Enquirer into the Causes of all the various <hi>Phenomena</hi> of the Civil, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> well as the Natural World; and that the behaviour, and Nature of these <hi>Blacks,</hi> pretending to be <hi>Physicians,</hi> may appear very strange, and un-accountable to your self, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> well as others, and put many in hazard to think, that a which Dr. <hi>Broun</hi> has offered in this matter, is nothing bu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Delusion, and Foppry: I judge it not Impertinent to of<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fer you my un-byassed Sentiments, in Relation to a clear and Rational Solution of these Mens Actions, and <hi>Pheno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mena;</hi> by giving a solid <hi>Hypothesis</hi> of their Nature, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by, I hope it will be plain, that the Dignity and Excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lency of an Improvement in Medicine, may not only be very consistent with snarlings and reproaches thrown thereupon by <hi>Interested</hi> and <hi>By-assed Physicians:</hi> but that all eminent Improvements are necessarily attended with
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:174794:22"/>that <hi>fate:</hi> so <hi>Philom,</hi> I realy think the World is not a little indebted to the Man, has the courage to make the venture to bring such to see the Light. For it is no more Plain, than it is Lamentable, that after the Laborious Penetrat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the Judicious, who raking the Bowels of Nature, has digged and refined any Improvement in the Cure of these Fevers, (perhaps of more value then all the Gold of the <hi>Indies</hi>) out of it's Natural Min and Oar, where it was hid and Inaccessable by the Block and Slug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard, yet before it can become acceptable, and of general use, it's put to encounter various Skirmisies, with the se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral Interests, Humors, yea <hi>Caprices</hi> of Men; and not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly every <hi>Dunce</hi> or <hi>Fop</hi> has an Itch to stain and sully that vertue he could never imitate, yea, scarce comprehend: yet he (as sufficiently qualified to encounterfit the <hi>Physici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an</hi> with the vulgar) is in a great measure capable to dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grace it, but even these that seem more Polished, &amp; Refined, and have Engrossed any Esteem, finding a new Title of ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plause in favours of the undertakers, necessarily follow such undertakings, shrewdly suspect it, as topping and veighing with their Reputation, to be at their Coast, and they Endangered thereby to have their merit Eclipsed; this raises such a Torrent of Heat and Envy against it, and its advancrs; that they are often made to stagger under them: and where the thing is so Conspicuou;, that they dare not meddle with it; and also finding it would be dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous and fatal to themselves, to make a quarrel of a mans vertue; they can, by means of their Art, and Authority, by a devilish Chimistry, Extract and Pick one out of the most Innocent Deportment to bespatter his Merit, and which will also serve them as a Cloak for their envy, and malice to the boot.</p>
                  <p>Thus men to save the borrowed Lustre of their Skill, sully their Candor: which altho a stain little Conspicuous
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:174794:23"/>is yet very dangerous; in <hi>Physicians</hi> for Ingenuity the como<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> spur to Industry, the Parent of Skill, being <hi>languid</hi> in then it must only be by the favour of <hi>Artifice,</hi> and Popular Erro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> without any solid worth, that such have thorow ti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <hi>(which vulgar opinion makes to ripen the most insipid them)</hi> scrambled up to any Eminency, and Enhaunced <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> Opinion of Experienced: But considering the false be tomed Reputation of these <hi>Parasits</hi> to fame, is like fai<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Money, which is brought in a night, and carried away th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> nixt: no wonder if vulgar humor, and applause that l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> set them on the Tottering Pinacle of unmerited esteem, as easily, but far more justly throw them down again. A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> indeed <hi>Philomath, I</hi> am tempted to tell you, that I this true worth, as it spares no Labour in acquiring, so saves no Coast to welcome true Improvements: and alwayes among the first that shakes hands with the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Whence it may be clear, that what ever <hi>benign aspect</hi> s<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap> Discoveries may carry to the World, yet if they bear <hi>reverse</hi> ought <hi>Malevolent</hi> to any Mans ill acquired Estee<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> or private Interest, a cold welcome is to good, nay a ve<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> hot one they must look for, from such Men: A clear e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dence (among any others) of this, was the Quarr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Contentions, &amp; Skirmishings, that arose about that mee Theoretical Improvement the circulation of the Blo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> And if it fare so here, how will it go, if an useful a practical Improvement offer to set up the Head, and Devils Game, as well as Mans be marred or these Tra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> or Snares that precipitate Men into the Kingdom of Da<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ness, be in danger to be removed, by any Considerable I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>provement in the Cure of these Formidable Fevers: the well see, as Dr. <hi>Broun</hi> Intimats further in hi Prefac<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> his Book: <q>That the Serpentine Brood, which is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> big with Malice, and Envious of the good of Men, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> and which was never more <hi>Dominant,</hi> than at this tim<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <pb n="17" facs="tcp:174794:23"/>will rase all the Corners of the Infernal Pit, for Venom to bespatter such a Project, and its Advancers with.</q> And so the Interest both of Men and Devils being at the stake, and both being attack't by this Improvement in <hi>Medicine,</hi> no wonder (as the <hi>French</hi> King and <hi>Turk</hi> have done) That Men and Devils Confederat against their Common Enemie Practical Improvement in Medicine.</p>
                  <p>Now how far all this may be applyed to Dr. <hi>Broun's</hi> opposers, any that will be at the pains to consider both his and their Papers, may very easily Judge: and if thereby, they clearly understand, that in advancing one of the most desirable Concerns of Men, he is as pertinent and solid in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> than they to depress it, turning quite from the Subject, are pregnant in vile <hi>Raili<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>, they will not hover long to give their Sentence.</p>
                  <p>After my former Letter emitted, and P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="7 letters">
                        <desc>〈7 letters〉</desc>
                     </gap>d in his Vindication, and in Answer to their Dialogue, and wherein the new Method was confirmed, by several Examples, it was thought Impertinency, was by sound Reasoning, so dashed out of Countenance, that it durst never appear any <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> that Errand.</p>
                  <p>But a 2d. Essay, a great deal more Impertinent, and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>famous than the former, made all Spectators understand, that no Humane Reason can tame <hi>Devilish Insolency,</hi> and that its as hard to check their scolding humors, as it was to Crub that brazen <hi>Zantipes</hi> Vein, whose unruly Member, after her Husband had several wayes (but all in vain) en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavoured to tame (she still calling him <hi>Lousie Rogue, Lousie Cuckold</hi>) at last he tryed her with ducking, but she put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting up both her hands, above the Water, and joyning the Nails of her Thumbs in a <hi>Crack-house</hi> posture, shewed how little she was dantoned. Even so these Men, when they are plunged over Head and Ears, in the derision of all sober Men, still attempt to give the most ridiculous vent
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:174794:24"/>to their Impertinent chatt. And withall the most favour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able Construction can be put upon their behavior seems this: These <hi>Blacks</hi> being such a waspish venomous Kind of Creatures, that when they are <hi>Irritate,</hi> (which is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes upon the appearance of any good to the World) the Venome <hi>Ferments</hi> and <hi>Works</hi> so within their Breasts, that it's ready to burst them, unless it break out with a <hi>Ratle</hi> at <hi>Railling Row:</hi> And notwithstanding <hi>Philomathes</hi> of all the venemous Eructations, and Floods of Viper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spaun, disgorged against Dr. <hi>Brown,</hi> by one of these <hi>Blacks,</hi> a bitter Viper: I heard say (which I think a very strange <hi>Phinomenon,</hi> that the <hi>Paroxisms</hi> and fits use to be so vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent in him still, that he is forced <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>, for without these, his <hi>Fits,</hi> like <hi>Gunpou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der,</hi> would make such a sorrowful parting betwean poor <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>, that the old sitten on Friends would ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver meet again, <hi>In speculis contemplare teipsum, Sin de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formis id morum pensato pulchritudine: audito multa, &amp; loquere pauca.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Mistake me not <hi>Philomath,</hi> as if <hi>I</hi> intended, transgres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing all humanity, to insult over any Mans <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>; no no, but being to solve the <hi>Phenomena</hi> of hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Wicked Actions, I am necessarily led to his Cursed Nature which having undouhtedly depraved <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> that lodges it (a discreet Guest indeed) no wonder it spares nothing it falls in hands with; and indeed I at<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tempted to take the Liberty to tell you <hi>Philomath,</hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> in my Opinion, lay a double Obligation on the Subject to Discretion and Vertue, and the vertue such, are endued with, not only gives a Proportionable Supply of their other Defects; but is also it self more Conspicuous and renders the Person more Amiable, so wicked <hi>Malice,</hi> making them justly more <hi>Odious</hi> and <hi>Abominable;</hi> makes Reasonably all their <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>, more Remarkable
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:174794:24"/>and that Common Saying, <hi>Cavendum ab his quos Deus &amp; natura notarunt,</hi> tho it may Justly have sometimes its ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptions, yet I think without breach of Charity, I may be Confident this Subject is none of them; for that Viper, without any Provocation, but his Conscience of honest Dr. <hi>Brown</hi>'s Ingenuity and Zeal for the Publick good (Which is <hi>I</hi> confess enough of Provocation to a malicious Brat) has by Printing, and all other wayes, imployed the utmost efforts of his Devilish Malice against him; as may be seem thorow all the Clubs Papers, whereof the bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terest and most invective Passages are the <hi>Hissings</hi> of this <hi>Viper,</hi> but ekpecially may be seen in the account he gives of my <hi>Lord Crichtouns</hi> Case, which like a venomous Serpent, in the pride of his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>, and Majesty of his Scales set<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting up his brisles, he fronts with this Malicious and Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nomous <hi>Hiss.</hi> (the baseness of <hi>Dolphintouns</hi> temper) as if he intended the effect of his malice should not die with Dr. <hi>Brown</hi> himself, but should descend to his Heirs, who appearantly may have the Designation of <hi>Dolphinton</hi> after him: But as Dr. <hi>Brown</hi> may justly glory in the Cause he suffers for, so may he do in the Instrument he suffers by; and he will be highly unjust both to his Cause and to Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>d, if he do not acquaint the World, that their Calum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap> may have the less Impression, what kind of Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="4 letters">
                        <desc>••••</desc>
                     </gap> (Malice being indeed the highest degree of Baseness) the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rincipal Adversaries of his Cause only are.</p>
                  <p>But considering, that the Devil rages most before he be cast out; this gives equally a presage of <hi>Dr. Brown</hi>'s suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cess, and makes the Efforts of his Instruments no wayes strange, or unaccountable. And in sum Dr. <hi>Brown</hi> needs not grudge his Enemies should Commence the most absolute Masters of <hi>Vile Railing,</hi> and <hi>Dis-ingenuous Cavelling,</hi> while he carries it in solid Reasoning, and safe Curing Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers, which hitherto have been so dismal to Mankind.
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:174794:25"/>But he may indeed Triumph, that all these <hi>Reproaches</hi> and <hi>Impertinencies</hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ar so clearly in reverse his hardy attempt for the publick good, which these <hi>Black Doctors</hi> construct as unluckie, first to <hi>Devils,</hi> and next to there Pettie, and private Interest. For any other grounds of their Calum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nious Libells, he defies them to make appear.</p>
                  <p>Moreover to show how sensible he is of the great bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit this Enemies have done him, by their Printed and ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bal Calumnies, whose perversness, adding difficulty to his Enterprizes, raise the Honour of his Success: and whose Ignorance Characterizing their Authors his Opposers, has for the most part enclined the Judicious to his side: this favour, tho done far beyond their Intension, he has more gratefully remunerate, with another not a whit less be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neficial to them, but far more meritorious, as being design<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and Intentional, and that is, albeit they have named him with all the Names, and Nick-names they pleased, yet he has still forborn to Name any of them, some thinks it's be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause he is ashamed of such antagonists, but I rather think it's out of Pity; least there should be a standing memori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al of their <hi>Rediculous Impertinencies</hi> and <hi>Folly,</hi> which would so conspicuously Blunder them, when their Embrace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing both his <hi>Theorie</hi> and <hi>Practice,</hi> becomes unavoidable, (as in all probability it shortly will) that it might really endanger them to hang themselves.</p>
                  <p>But there is one of them that <hi>I</hi> am truly sorry for, because he has had the hard fate to prove so Publick a <hi>Tool</hi> to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cente the Malicious Contrivances of the more <hi>Politick</hi> pates of that <hi>Crew,</hi> that a Honourable retreat to him, is scarce Possible: for that Man not being able to Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tribute any of the least pittance to that stock of sorry will their <hi>Pamphlets</hi> are stuffed with, was content for his part to Contribute his Pains o drudge at the Press for the rest: and also to do the Office of the Coal-stealler Boyes, in
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:174794:25"/>dispersing their Malicious Papers: Alace, the <hi>club</hi> has done with that <hi>poor soul,</hi> as the willie <hi>Pug</hi> does with the <hi>Cat,</hi> with whole Fees he scapes his <hi>Chesnuts</hi> out of the Fire (and I believe the <hi>Monkey</hi> was handling the <hi>Cat</hi> of <hi>Smel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holm,</hi> so when she spake wonders) and to Cool his burnt <hi>Paves,</hi> the Good-man of the <hi>Club,</hi> who had never any great Kindness for him before, (when he thought it not worth his pains to go himself, being in the midst of the Storm) sent the <hi>Poor Singed Doctor</hi> a highland Journey for him, where he would get Snow-Water, but a <hi>Green Burn,</hi> like a <hi>Green Wound</hi> is half whole, behold the end, and that the <hi>Titling</hi> was not sent along with the <hi>Gouk,</hi> came from the Good-man's tender care of the poor <hi>Titling,</hi> who would have cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly been lost in a wreath of Snow, if he had gone.</p>
                  <p>There is another effect their <hi>Pamphlets</hi> has had, which is very pleasant, and it's this: The <hi>Apothecaries</hi> finding the <hi>Club</hi> had contrived their Papers so abominably nau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seous, that they would easily turn many tender Stomachs begun to suspect the <hi>club</hi> had a design against their Trade, and that they might perhaps serve their Patients with Vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitors, and Purges of such stuff, giving them so many Leaves out of one of their <hi>Pamphlets</hi> for a Dose, according to their Constitutions and Deseases. And this Jealousie was so warm among the <hi>Apothecaries Boyes,</hi> that it had almost raised them in a Tumult to have <hi>Rabled</hi> the <hi>Club.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>As on the one hand, the <hi>Black Drs. Scurilous Pamphlets does,</hi> in the Eyes of all Judicious Men, evince them the most foolish and malicious of all Men, so on the other other hand, when they come to any thing that's serious, and offers to reach a hit at Dr. <hi>Brown</hi>'s new <hi>Theory</hi> or <hi>Practice,</hi> they discribe themselves the most Ignorant in the World: and therefore their last Essay was look't on as worthy of no other regard but Scorn and Contempt, yet because the usurped and fals bottomed <hi>Authority</hi> of a great
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:174794:26"/>many <hi>Senior Dunces,</hi> of that <hi>gang;</hi> whose Credit lye<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> undoubtedly in <hi>P</hi> and on this Plea, does amuse the Igno<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ant vulgar, who, perhaps making the far greatest part o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> the World deserve not a little to be Considered and Satis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied, to the end that they may take better measure where to repose the trust of so great Concerns: Therefor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> it was not thought altogether Improper, to give a furthe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> and clearer Representation of that <hi>Theory,</hi> and the piti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Reasons brought by the <hi>Learned Club</hi> against it.</p>
                  <p>How rediculous then are these men by a f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> impertinent and incoherent Assertions, bearing in the Front only (it's certain) without any other proof, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> evidence, and these so mingled with bitter invictives th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> are able to quite choak the most clear Reasoning in the World. How ridiculous are they, I say, to attempt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> overturn an <hi>Hypothesis,</hi> not taken up <hi>gratis,</hi> but rivet<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> and founded by a solid Reasoning on the most part of t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> principal <hi>Phenomena</hi> occurring about the <hi>Aeconomie</hi> Mans Bodie, and these so clearly solved thereby, and ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> so neatly to quadrat therewith, as Dr. <hi>Brown</hi>'s <hi>The<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi> of Fevers in his <hi>schedule,</hi> seems to have done; Indeed <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> their manner of Impugning it, they assure the World, th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> they never understood it; for any that will be at the pa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> to Consider it closely (what's in Debate being ev<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> mans near concern) will find it an <hi>Hypothesis</hi> that's cle<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly demonstrat to include that <hi>Metaphysical</hi> Considerati<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> as being most suitable to the Perfection of the <hi>animal Ae<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nomie,</hi> and <hi>Mechanism;</hi> and as seeming exceedingly su<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to the design of the <hi>Architeck,</hi> and an <hi>Hypothe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi> which has also its <hi>Parallel</hi> in other Actions of the <hi>Ae<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nomie,</hi> such as the contraction and delatation of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> of the Eye, and in Actions from <hi>Irritation,</hi> commonly eled.</p>
                  <pb n="23" facs="tcp:174794:26"/>
                  <p>An <hi>Hypothesis</hi> that quadrats with the <hi>Composition</hi> of the <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>lood,</hi> which is made up of many little <hi>Globules,</hi> whose <hi>Number, Bulk</hi> or <hi>Figure</hi> may easily be supposed to become <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>itiated.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A Hypothesis</hi> having the <hi>Concatnation</hi> of the <hi>Procatar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ick</hi> and <hi>external Causes</hi> of <hi>Fevers</hi> favouring it, such all<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>wayes being apt to produce viscosity and grosness in the <hi>Blood</hi> and <hi>Humors.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>An <hi>Hypothesis</hi> that's founded in the Consequences of that great, tho <hi>Insensible Evacuation</hi> of <hi>Perspiration</hi> l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>sed, and in the <hi>Nature</hi> and <hi>Lesion</hi> of <hi>Digestion</hi> of the Stomach; also both the frequent Causes of <hi>Viscosity</hi> and <hi>Fevers.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>A <hi>Hypothesis,</hi> by which are solved clearly the natural <hi>Penomena</hi> in <hi>Fevers,</hi> such as <hi>Frequency</hi> of the <hi>Pulsie, Heat, Inquietness, Pains, Anxieties, delirium,</hi> and <hi>Spots.</hi> Where, also the <hi>Phenomena</hi> of helpers in Fevers stand clearly of its side, as first Blooding, and the various <hi>Phenomenae</hi> occuring about it, <hi>solved conform thereto, and made to confirm it.</hi> As also that <hi>Magtsterial</hi> Remedy, of Purg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ng, Clearing and Confirming that <hi>Hypothesis,</hi> with the use and benefit of the <hi>Paregorick.</hi> and <hi>quieting</hi> Medicine, <hi>Homologating</hi> the same.</p>
                  <p>Where also it is shewed how the Benefit from <hi>volatile,</hi> and fixed Salts, and <hi>testaceous Concrets,</hi> exceedingly fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours this <hi>Hypothesis,</hi> and also how the henefit of <hi>Cup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings Leiches</hi> and <hi>Frictions</hi> confirm it. A <hi>Hypothesis</hi> which has cleared the hurt of the <hi>meer Diaphoretique method in Fevers,</hi> and where many other <hi>Phenomena</hi> of <hi>Hurters</hi> are fully solved conform thereto.</p>
                  <p>Whosoever then shall think that an <hi>Hypothesis,</hi> more clearly founded than ever, I think any yet has been, in reference to that subject of Fevers, and which has never been Comprehended, or understood by them, far less Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sidered or Expended so, as to make them Capble to
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:174794:27"/>Impung it) should be overturned by the dash of a fe<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap> Impertinent In-consequential and False Assertions, co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cluding with all nothing, against the <hi>Hypothesis,</hi> they ma<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap> als well think <hi>Arthurs Seat</hi> will be overturned by a fo<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap> Mol-hills casten up therein, by the poor blind <hi>Moles▪</hi> and this I think, will fall in nobodies head, but these th<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap> are fully as Ignorant, blind and <hi>Blockish,</hi> as these blac<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <hi>Doctors.</hi> And now <hi>Phil.</hi> civility obliges me to usher in wh<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap> I am now to take up your time with, with a craving Par<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>don, knowing you can bestow your minute better than o<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap> such Trash: for no better Epithet can I give what they hav<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap> said against Dr. <hi>Browns</hi> Theory, as you shall easily per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive, by and by, and is mentioned in the <hi>Page</hi> 13. and 14 of their Answer.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>First,</hi> They say <hi>That every Part that is Contracted h<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap> an Inate faculty to perform that Action which is done, by the Influx of the Animal Spirits into the Fibres.</hi> This wi<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap> prove a direct Contradiction, an Action to depend on <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <hi>Inate faculty</hi> of the Part, and yet to be done by the <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>flux</hi> of the <hi>Animal Spirits,</hi> which are quite <hi>Extraneou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi> thereto, and in a perpetual Flux, seems clearly repugnant and als absurd as to say, that a <hi>Miln-wheel</hi> hath an <hi>Ina<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap> Faculty</hi> to move about, which done by the falling o<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap> the Water upon it.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. They say next, <hi>All Parts when delated do suffer eve<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap> violence from the Humors, and what els they contain,</hi> doe<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap> the Dilatation of the Brain, or Breast come from vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence I pray, of what, yea does the heart it self suffer vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence from the Blood. These Men are so Giddy themselves that they labour to turn all the Moderat and Benigne Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions in Nature making Life, into reeling, violent, and Preter-natural ones, they are so much in Love with Jar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, that they dream of nothing but Force and Discord.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. They say, <hi>That the ventricles of the heart are of the
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:174794:27"/>same substance with the Inner coates of the Arteries and Veins</hi> (which is scarce sence) <hi>and that they are sensible of Irritation, that the Dilatation of the Heart, the weight, the distention through effervescence of the Blood, doth Ir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritate it:</hi> To say the Truth, this Principal of Irritation, which they most foolishly make the Cause of the <hi>natural motion</hi> of the Heart, must have its rise from that Irrita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion raised in themselves, upon the appearance of Truth and Light, whereby, like men that have the <hi>Yellow Jan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dice,</hi> who think all things yellow, they think every thing Ir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritate, when they are so themselves. And there is no doubt, if ye will ask them, ye will likewise find they fancy, that the Sun, Moon and Stars, and all other motions <hi>in the universe</hi> move from Irritation, yea, <hi>bark</hi> and <hi>Irr</hi> too when their <hi>Chimerical Hypothesis</hi> is Impugned, and that the <hi>Harmony</hi> of the <hi>Spheres</hi> must turn <hi>Jargon</hi> as well as the Heart for Company:</p>
                  <p>Now how Rediculous is this to any Person, but a little ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted with <hi>Speculation,</hi> it being plain that the <hi>Contraction</hi> of the <hi>Muscles,</hi> is the more natural of the two Motions: For the Resolution of the oposite <hi>Muscle</hi> is still followed with the Contraction of the other, and the Heart being a <hi>Muscle,</hi> the <hi>Contraction</hi> thereof, rather than the <hi>Dilata<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> is a Natural Motion, and therefore does depend on no <hi>Irritation,</hi> but is the perpetual Law of the <hi>Aeconomy</hi> sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>servient to the great end of Distribution of the nourish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to the whole: and is no more from <hi>Irritation</hi> than the like Conveyance of the Nutrition in <hi>Vegetables</hi> is. Would it not be brave <hi>Philosophy</hi> to say, the Sap goes from the Root of the Plant to the Branches by <hi>Irritation.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And further the quantity of Blood squized into the Heart, suppose a <hi>dram</hi> is as far from Irritating it, as a conveni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent Portion of Meat received into the <hi>Stomack,</hi> which is not sent out till after <hi>Digestion,</hi> but then by no Irritation.</p>
                  <pb n="26" facs="tcp:174794:28"/>
                  <p>As also the <hi>Effervescence</hi> of the Blood either in a Natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral or preter-natural state is a stale Error, reasonably Exploded by Dr. <hi>Brown,</hi> according to the best new Authors, as <hi>Blancard, Bohn, Brounerus, Charleton.</hi> And <hi>Effer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vecence</hi> being an <hi>Intestine Commotion</hi> of the minute Parts of Bodies, which most frequently, happens by <hi>Hetero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geneous mixtures.</hi> It can never be reasonably said to be, but where the Senses discover it: pray with which o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> the Senses did ever these acute Drs. discover the same in the Blood: if all the World must believe against their Sences with these subtile <hi>Doctors,</hi> pray let them usher in <hi>Transubstantiation</hi> next, for they have broken the grea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> But that kept it out.</p>
                  <p n="4">4ly, They say, <hi>This Irritation makes the Heart Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tract it self, without respect to a final Cause.</hi> This is a clear Repugnancy for all <hi>Irritations</hi> in the Parts, when they are, are <hi>Preter-natural</hi> Motions, from <hi>Preter-natura<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi> Causes, and are raised to rid the Partes offended of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <hi>Irritating</hi> Matter, and here Nature may be said not very Improperly to Act for an end, yea, and if such an <hi>Irritation</hi> as this were Competent to the heart, in its Natural Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, it clearly implayes the like acting for an end, tho an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> end quite distinct from that Implyed in Dr. <hi>Brown</hi>'s <hi>Vin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicatorie schedule:</hi> for indeed their <hi>Hypothesis</hi> obliges the Heart to throw out the Blood to be rid of it, as a <hi>Griev<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance,</hi> which is no sooner done, than like <hi>Sysiphus</hi> Labour malicious Nature sends in another <hi>Dash</hi> or <hi>Squirt</hi> to v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> it, and this being perpetual puts the Heart in a Continua<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <hi>Chaff</hi> at the poor <hi>Blood,</hi> which comes no sooner into the <hi>Heart,</hi> but as a troublesome <hi>Guest,</hi> is immediatly thrown out into the <hi>Arteries, Irritating</hi> them likewise, which pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sently sends it a packing into the <hi>Veins,</hi> which having al<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> little Kindness for it are at <hi>Continual</hi> toil to send it back again to the <hi>Heart,</hi> where it gets als little rest; One would
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:174794:28"/>think the <hi>poor Blood</hi> is followed with <hi>Hue</hi> and <hi>Cry,</hi> and that nature is at a <hi>Fox hunting</hi> with it from <hi>Hill</hi> to <hi>Dail, back</hi> and <hi>forward,</hi> and at Death the <hi>Blood,</hi> having lost its <hi>Legs,</hi> is Catched: and so the <hi>Game</hi> ends.</p>
                  <q>Risum teneatis amici.</q>
                  <p>But to be serious about their <hi>Irritation</hi> and <hi>Vio lnce,</hi> there two principles of <hi>Natural</hi> Motion, <hi>I</hi> pray you <hi>Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty Club,</hi> what violents the Heart of <hi>Dilatation</hi> and <hi>Irri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tats</hi> it to <hi>Contraction,</hi> when it beats, being out of the Body of some <hi>Animals,</hi> without any Blood, coming in, or going out. This one Instance, if they had read Dr. <hi>Brown</hi>'s Book with any more Attention then the Parats speaks Words, would never have suffered them to slipt so fouly. Thete offering to Answer the Book being an Affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation that they have read it, I will not offer to Contradict it, as being loath to call them both Fools and Liars, but one of them they must surely be.</p>
                  <p>Next they say, <hi>that the Pulse that strickes the Finger, is nothing but the Dilatation of the Arteries, occasioned by the Contraction of the heart</hi> which is granted, <hi>Then they add, for</hi> Dr. Brown <hi>to say, that in a Fever, the Pulses are more frequent, and yet to say the Circuit Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Blood is more slow is great non-sense.</hi> O brutish Ignorance, for first, this last Assertion is no wayes consequen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiall to the former, tho they bring it in Consequence there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of; and next, and that considers the matter will find, the last Assertion a plain falshood for to say in a Fever, the Circuit Motions of the Blood is more slow, and yet the Pulse more frequent, is als good Sense, as to say, that the <hi>stroakes</hi> of a <hi>Pump</hi> may be doubled, and yet the Water come out more slowly than at other times it does by single <hi>stroaks.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And this <hi>Phenomenon</hi> in the Pump is obvious to the Senses, with its Cause, for if either the Liquor <hi>Pumped</hi> be
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:174794:29"/>more <hi>viscuous,</hi> or if the <hi>Top-hole</hi> be not clear, the fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent agitation of the <hi>Pump</hi> will pour out less Liquor than the moderat working thereof, when the Liquor is suffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently tenuious and thin, and the Top-hole clear. As also the short and thick stroaks of a <hi>Pump</hi> pours out less Wat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er then long and rare stroaks do; even so the Pulse of the Heart and Arteries, altho more than usual frequent, may convey less Blood into the Veins, when the Blood it sel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> is more gross, or the Passages betwixt them obstructed, or not sufficiently Patent: then a lesser frequency of the Pulse does, when the Blood, or Passages are not under the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> Faults. And it's clear that the <hi>Pulse</hi> is less frequent it health, because, after the <hi>Arteries</hi> by their Dilatation have beat the touch they are <hi>Contracted</hi> very near their Centre and do expel into the Veins almost all the Contained Blood so, in the subsequent <hi>Dilatation,</hi> as moving more space <hi>viz.</hi> From the <hi>Centre</hi> to the <hi>Circum<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>erence,</hi> they mos<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> of necessity take more time to Dilate, and Consequently seldomer beat the touch, than in the Case where th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Blood is with difficulty admitted from the <hi>Arteries,</hi> int<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> the <hi>Veins,</hi> because then they Contract Less, much of the Contained Blood remaining, hinders their Coats from com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing so near their Centre, as in the former Case, and s<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> their Terms or Bounds of Contraction and Dilatation be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing near, they are moved from the Bound of their Contrac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, unto the bound of their <hi>Dilatation,</hi> &amp; strick the Touc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> sooner, and in less time, &amp; so the space betwixt every Pul<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> is Commensurat by, and proportionat to the greater o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> lesser Contraction, a great <hi>Contraction</hi> making still a ra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <hi>Pulse,</hi> and a lesser, a frequent one: And a clear resem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blance of this is seen in <hi>Respiration,</hi> which in the Natural mode is more slow, and more Aire received into the Lung<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> and more expelled at every turn of Respiration, and the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> the Breast also Dilated and Contracted more, than in fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:174794:29"/>and short <hi>Respiration,</hi> where less Air is received, and less expelled at every turn, and the Breast also less Dilated and Cnntracted: much like the former <hi>Phenomenon,</hi> in the <hi>Pump,</hi> where short &amp; thick strokes poureth out less Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, than long and rare ones do. And in the Motion of the Blood, the <hi>Heart</hi> furnishes the quantity to the <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teries,</hi> in proportion only, as the <hi>Arteries</hi> are Emptied into the Veins, which in the Natural State, when the Circuit Motion is performed <hi>Vegetly,</hi> may be a <hi>Dram</hi> or more, but when that Motion is <hi>Torpid</hi> and <hi>Loitering,</hi> and the Blood with difficulty passes from the <hi>Arteries</hi> into the <hi>Veins,</hi> the Heart at every <hi>Pulse</hi> conveyes so much Blood into the <hi>Arteries</hi> only, as they by emptying themselves in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Veins have made room for, which may sometimes be very little; for in <hi>Agonizing</hi> or <hi>Expiring</hi> Persons, where the <hi>Pulse</hi> beats the Touch with the greatest frequency imaginable, it's because the <hi>Contraction</hi> is so little and <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sequently</hi> the blood squized out of the <hi>Arteries,</hi> so very little, that the <hi>Dilatation</hi> is again immediately felt on the Touch: and this is so frequent, that it is rather called a <hi>Tremulous</hi> Motion of the <hi>Arteries,</hi> than a distinct <hi>Pulse</hi> consisting of sensible <hi>Contraction</hi> and <hi>Dilatation,</hi> But ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the <hi>Hypothesis</hi> of the <hi>Grand Club,</hi> the Blood should then <hi>Circulat</hi> more <hi>rapidly,</hi> than which there can be no thing invented more <hi>Ridiculous.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>In Consequence of all, by the leave of that <hi>Learned Crew of Ignorant Black Doctors,</hi> it's very good Sense, and Reason both to say, that the frequenter the Pulse beats, the circuit Motion of the Blood may not only be more slow, but also, by the multitude of the <hi>Phenomena</hi> before men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned, solved by <hi>Dr. Brown,</hi> confirming this <hi>Hypothesis,</hi> is proven actually to be more slow. And also by the same Leave, it may not be impertinent to alledge, since Nature does not accelerat Motion in Vain, That, that <hi>Frequency,</hi>
                     <pb n="30" facs="tcp:174794:30"/>beside what is illustrat before, is excited also, to overcome the slowness and resistance betwixt the <hi>Arteries</hi> and <hi>Veins,</hi> as is at more length held forth by Dr <hi>Brown</hi> in <hi>his Schedule.</hi> And how the <hi>Progress</hi> and <hi>Circulation</hi> of the blood it made thorow all he <hi>Meanders</hi> and <hi>Narrow windings,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt the <hi>Arteries</hi> and <hi>Veins,</hi> and that in so short a time as Nature requires it in the <hi>Natural State</hi> to <hi>Circle</hi> about (which according to Dr. <hi>Lower,</hi> is less than the 6th part of an hour) is very wonderful and <hi>difficult</hi> to conceive; and without very much <hi>Elevating</hi> and Abstracting our thoughts we can scarce have any Satisfaction of it: and therfore th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Circulation of the blood was opposed by many, because they thought it impossible; but to supperadd to that <hi>stu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penduous</hi> Motion, so inconceivable a <hi>Propertie,</hi> or <hi>accident,</hi> as an <hi>Augmentation</hi> or <hi>Increase,</hi> the mind must suffer strange <hi>Tortune</hi> and <hi>Rack</hi> to Comprehend it: but how easily may that Motion be cnnceived to be Diminished.</p>
                  <p>It was indeed the Inconceivableness of the <hi>Rapidity</hi> o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> the Suns motion by the common <hi>Hypothesis,</hi> which made <hi>Copernicus</hi> six the Sun and send the <hi>Earth</hi> a <hi>Rambling</hi> about it: By which all the <hi>Phenomena</hi> were als-wel solved and a more comprehensible and satisfieing <hi>Notion</hi> of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Motion established to the boot: But these blacks make so much Noise with their Bable, of Rapidity, Violence, and <hi>Irritation,</hi> that certainly they will fright <hi>Phaetions</hi> Horse<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> whom <hi>Copernicus</hi> had quietly stabled up, and send them <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <hi>packing</hi> again about the World, and then they must fetch <hi>Vul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>can</hi> to nail down the Earth to its fixed Centure again, for i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> the <hi>Sun</hi> and <hi>Earth</hi> come to shoulder others in their <hi>Orbs<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi> they may give a <hi>terrible Jolt.</hi> And if the <hi>Rapidity</hi> of the <hi>Suns</hi> motion be inconceiveable still let the Sun look to that, as well as the Blood.</p>
                  <p>And with all such a <hi>Fals Notion</hi> as this of the <hi>Circula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> of the <hi>Blood</hi> augmented does not stay heer as being a
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:174794:30"/>meer <hi>Theoretical Error</hi> and of no further purport▪ But <hi>Alace</hi> it puts the <hi>Artiest</hi> in his practice upon the most dangerous measures, and <hi>Precipitates</hi> him into the most Fatal Errors, as impelling him to put <hi>Clogs</hi> and <hi>Barrs</hi> on that motion, wherein consists Life, often already too much <hi>Loittering</hi> and <hi>Fetterred.</hi> And is as <hi>pernicious</hi> as it would be <hi>Rediculous</hi> to see these witty <hi>Doctors</hi> load a Horse that can scarce go Empty, for fear of his running away.</p>
                  <p>Moreover, as <hi>Dr. Broun</hi> has observed in the Preface to his Book, this Circulation of the Blood did strangely lie in the dark for many Ages, and was long opposed, because it was thought impossible, (what then would these opposers have said to hear its augmented now) and also it was opposed by others, because altho it seemed to Illustrate the <hi>Theorie</hi> of <hi>Medecine,</hi> yet it made no improvement in the practice thereof.</p>
                  <p>But now by this <hi>Theorie</hi> of <hi>Dr. Brouns,</hi> that noble dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coverie is not only <hi>Confirmed,</hi> and not everted (as these men throgh the Grossest mistake ignorantly assert) but also is delivered from that reproach of <hi>useless.</hi> For he clearly does evince this motion of the Blood <hi>Diminished,</hi> and its slowness depending upon the <hi>Grosness,</hi> to be the nearest Cause, if not of most diseases, yet <hi>of Continual Fevers:</hi> And further since he has showen by what <hi>Complication</hi> and <hi>Concatenation</hi> of other Causes, this nearest Cause by <hi>O<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der</hi> or <hi>Congress</hi> is fomented: How many solid and fruitful <hi>Jndications,</hi> altogether formerly lying in the Dark, may there be drawn from thence: Especially seing we may be furnished with sufficient means to satissie these <hi>Jndica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions:</hi> And that either by <hi>Correcting, Intercepting,</hi> or <hi>Eradicating these Causes,</hi> being destinctly known. And so this <hi>Theorie</hi> seemes not only to be clear in it self, but also leads to the <hi>Practical Improvement</hi> of the <hi>Circulation</hi> of the <hi>Blood:</hi> And notwithstanding all the applause the <hi>Circulation of</hi> the <hi>Blood,</hi> has deservedly met with in the
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:174794:31"/>World, this <hi>Theorie</hi> is as much preferable to it, as the be<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>t <hi>Practical Improvement</hi> is preferable to a meer <hi>Theore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tical</hi> one, and in consequence every mans <hi>Demerit</hi> In rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to the <hi>Advancing and Opposing</hi> this most <hi>Plausible</hi> and <hi>Ʋseful Theorie</hi> of Dr. <hi>Brouns,</hi> must be <hi>Commensurable</hi> according to the value, it will really be found to be of.</p>
                  <p>As for the rest of their <hi>Assertions,</hi> viz, That <hi>it's alwayes a received Opinion that heat in Fevers is the effect of rapid motion of the Blood.</hi> Many of the best Authors, as <hi>Silvius, Willes Paracelsus</hi> and <hi>Helmont,</hi> &amp;c. Attribute it to other causes, and albeit it had been a Commonly received Opinion, does that hinder but that it may be a <hi>Vulgar Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror,</hi> and as they do not attaque, one of Dr. <hi>Broun</hi>'s rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons against it, so they do not bring one for it: Then they make a digression into the cause of heat in an <hi>Inflammation,</hi> In handling of which they first say, <hi>that the Blood is then Extravasated,</hi> and immediatly they say, <hi>that the Ateries are distended therewith,</hi> pray let them reconcile these. And next they say, <hi>The quantity of Blood is the cause of heat in an Inflamation,</hi> then which there can be nothing more false, for in an, <hi>Anewrisma,</hi> which is a bag of <hi>Arterial, Bloo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi> with a continual <hi>Pulsation,</hi> and the part has far more Blood then an <hi>Inflammation</hi> or ane <hi>Aerisipelas,</hi> but far less heat: Yea none at all beyond the rest of the Skin.</p>
                  <p>And in fine their whole Chat for reasoning. I cannot call it is so <hi>pitiful</hi> and impertinent and nothing conclusive that it appears they not only want the sence to lay down any plausible <hi>Hipothesis</hi> of their own, but that they never have Considered, Traced, nor Expended Dr. <hi>Broun</hi>'s Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clusions: Far less can it be expected they will confute them. Which, albeit they had been false, could not have been di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stinctly done but in a Book at least three times as big as his, yet this curtaleing Club pretends to do it in less than one Leafe.</p>
                  <pb n="33" facs="tcp:174794:31"/>
                  <p>As to what the <hi>Black Drs,</hi> alledge <hi>there is nothing an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swered to these matters of Fact, wherewith Dr,</hi> Broun <hi>stands Branded in their Dialogue</hi> It's answered first, that the <hi>Black Mouth'd</hi> Drs. Tongues are no <hi>Slander: Next</hi> it seems the heat of <hi>Black</hi>'s Furie has drained his <hi>Common sense</hi> and Reason, for did not my former Letter t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ll him that their <hi>Dialogue</hi> contained nothing but <hi>Lies, Cavells</hi> and <hi>Calumnies:</hi> How come they now to ask what answer can be given to them. It seems these <hi>Black</hi>'s has as little Skill in <hi>Common sence,</hi> as in <hi>Physick.</hi> For since these Slan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders were denyed, they should in the 2d, Pamphlet have brought their proof and witness, since <hi>Philander</hi>'s denyal is as good as either Fool <hi>Sanders,</hi> or Fool <hi>Mathews</hi> Affirmation.</p>
                  <p>That where the Black sayes, since Dr, <hi>Brown subjected his Book to the consideration of all Ingenuous and Faithful Physicians, now he has got the Sentiments of some of them, little to his Satisfaction.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>First, who gives <hi>Black</hi> this Testimony but himself, and dare such R<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>gues Arrogate that name that dare not appear but in Masquerade. These Censurers for all their disguise will be found out by their sent to be no better than some piece of flat, <hi>Corum Bobus</hi> or viper riden Fopp, and some ill natur'd <hi>Brate,</hi> whom God and Nature has not made so <hi>Ridiculous</hi> as his <hi>Serpentine Viperish</hi> Humor has made <hi>Ignominious:</hi> And their Opinions of it is so much to Dr. <hi>Browns</hi> satisfaction, that he would never have been well satisfied with his Book, if these silly and ill hewen p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>eces had not been mad at it. But ask what testi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony Dr. <hi>Bt.</hi> and Dr, <hi>B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>e</hi> gave of the Book, to many famous witnesses, who yet can bear Testimony of it, and whose Names <hi>I</hi> could easily mention; but I suppose these Physicians will minch yet nothing of what was their Sentiments of it. Not that <hi>I</hi> mention this to <hi>Establish</hi> any more Reputation
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:174794:32"/>to <hi>Dr, Browns</hi> Book, then every reader shall be convinc<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap> is due to it, none having the power to <hi>Monopolize</hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> mens Judgments, so great a Fool is <hi>Black</hi> to attempt it.</p>
                  <p>As for these passages mentioned in their Dialogue an<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap> taken out of Dr, <hi>Browns</hi> Schedule, and called either no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>sence or Contradiction; It's answered Dr, <hi>Black</hi> has he<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap> proven very honest, and appears in his true Jugling Natu<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap> for any that will be at the pains to compare these passag<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap> with Dr, <hi>Brouns</hi> Book will find, that the most part of the<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap> are wrong set down or Courtailled, all of them, the three <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> and Cohe-rence of the discourse broken and interrupted.</p>
                  <p>And for that one sentence concerning acuteness, whi<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap> is taxed of nonsence Dr. <hi>Brown</hi> has his end, when the<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap> break their Shines on it, for when he is speaking of acutn<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap> necessary in a Physician, he thought fit to wrap up the m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter in a littly obscurity to be a <hi>Touchstone for a sufficient ac<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>men,</hi> and so those Blocks having deservedly stumbled <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> it, is a clear concession they are <hi>Incapable</hi> to penetrate <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> greater mysteries, and withal there are such manifest Co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tradictions in their Dialogue, that he that runs may re<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap> (for indeed few will stay long to read it) This one I sh<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap> among many others name, first they represent <hi>Dr. Bro<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi> such a stranger to learning, that he has never piped beyo<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap> the Title pages of Books, and a little after, they repres<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap> him to have stollen his Book out osten or twelve of t<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap> best <hi>Phisiological Authors</hi> in Physick. —. Dialogue pa<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>As</hi> to what the <hi>Black Dr.</hi> sayes <hi>that his old met<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap> approved by thousands for many hundreds of years, sho<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap> not be overturned to establish a new one with such manif<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap> Contradiction.</hi> Now <hi>Black</hi> speaks like himself, a dow<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>right <hi>sitten on brate</hi> in Medicine that will allow no <hi>advan<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi> or <hi>Improvement</hi> therein for hundreds of years, But, ho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ever long his method his been used, it has been sut<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap> very little succesful, especially since I was any thi<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="35" facs="tcp:174794:32"/>capable to make observation about things, and about three years agoe as I remember there was a <hi>Physician</hi> in town Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fessed that of 30 Patients he had that year of <hi>Fevers,</hi> only two of them recovered. And if <hi>Black</hi> deny this, there will be a list of their Names gotten and publ shed, and at that same time fevers treated by the new method were all happily Cured.</p>
                  <p>And tho <hi>Fevers</hi> be not now so frequent as then, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps many of them being frighted away or <hi>Metamorphosed</hi> into other shapes, because of this Civil war among Physicians, yet it, very plain, that to diseases formerly called <hi>Fevers,</hi> our Physicians now give the name of <hi>Surfeits, Colds, Rheu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>tismes</hi> Feverish fitts, and I do not know what But what effect this is like to have ye may judge by this story, one <hi>Apothecary</hi> came to a <hi>Dr,</hi> with a great complaint, saying their Trade would be all ruined, for their Patients and Friends, said they could take no thing the <hi>Physician</hi> had pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scribed him, for they told the <hi>Physician</hi> mistook their Disease, because when they were sure it was a Fever he called it they do not know what.</p>
                  <p>And indeed <hi>Philom</hi> all ordinary Fevers are als well known, and their Intention and remission, to any intelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent <hi>Patient</hi> or by stander as to a <hi>Physician:</hi> And that by their <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>nsible symptoms, such <hi>as</hi> Heat, <hi>Drought, Pain</hi> of the Back, or <hi>Head,</hi> a Frequent pulse, and <hi>most part</hi> sudden in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vasion of the Desease, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Tho in some <hi>Fevers</hi> that are called <hi>Malignant,</hi> the ordinary symptoms are ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther mild or absent, or bears no proportion, here the <hi>Physician</hi> has only the priveledge to be <hi>Ʋmpire</hi> and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ole arbitrator: But where ever he usurp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> over Peoples senses and reason, all he gains is to become himself redi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culous, Yea some Physician lately in Town, profest Enemies <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>o this Method, having cured Fevers by the same, but un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the name of another Desease, when the Patient after <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> was recovered, heard what the Drs. called his Disease,
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:174794:33"/>he was almost frighted into the Fever again, thinking what a danger he had been in, when his <hi>Physician</hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>il tooke his Disease, but at length: he <hi>Apothicary</hi> came, and Cured him, by telling him the <hi>Knack,</hi> how after this manner they concealed the new Cure of Fevers.</p>
                  <p>Where the <hi>Black Dr.</hi> sayes, <hi>there are only</hi> 2 or 3. <hi>Young Physicians that follow, or favour that new Practice <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>f curing Fevers.</hi> It may be Answered, that there are more that favour it, than follow it, perchance hindered by a too ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil Veneration to Elder <hi>Physicians,</hi> (that is more for fear of their ill than any hope of their good,) who perhaps may get that we like the Pharisees, for neither following it themselves, nor suffering others, and these that now owne it, having done it, before ever they knew Dr. <hi>Brown,</hi> did equally manifest their accomplisht <hi>Sagacity,</hi> in their being among the first that perceived, and descryed <hi>Improve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments,</hi> and their <hi>Ingenuity,</hi> that for no <hi>Base</hi> and <hi>By-ends,</hi> nor <hi>Slavish Veneration</hi> can be brought to pass over, or ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glect them, and further these, tho young in Years are capable to give good proof both by this, and their other Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, that they are <hi>Mature</hi> in accomplishments, far be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond these <hi>Duarf shits▪</hi> and <hi>sitten</hi> on Brats in Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cine, who have made no advancement therein, in Propor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to their Age; And that Dr. <hi>Brown</hi>'s Enemies must be such a <hi>Fry,</hi> appears by their ill natur'd Papers, <hi>Dwarfs</hi> and <hi>Elfs</hi> being still the most Curled Creatures in the World.</p>
                  <p>The <hi>Black</hi> Dr. Moreover sayes, that <hi>it's not reasonable to believe all these Persons Instanced by me in my former Letter had Fevers, since Dr.</hi> Brown <hi>had the Impudence to call that a Fever, which two of the most eminent Physicians in</hi> Edinburgh <hi>said was none; what will be then say, where he is sole Phisician.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>It's Answered, if by <hi>Eminent,</hi> they mean such as carry
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:174794:33"/>that respect to other <hi>Physicians;</hi> that the <hi>Cooklefts</hi> and <hi>Garrets</hi> do to Houses which are alwayes worst furnisht, or which (like the Weather-Cock above the Churches) serve only to tell how the Winds of fame <hi>Blow.</hi> It's easily grant <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nd, that such <hi>Eminencies</hi> may state themselves in that Oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sition to him, either out of <hi>Design, Malice,</hi> or <hi>Ignorance.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>But since there is no Persons, or Case named, Dr. <hi>Brown</hi> is not concerned to do it: but if any other will do it. I hope there may, for the good of the World, be given such a clear Representation of the matter, as giving every man his due, will lend such a <hi>blow</hi> to their <hi>Eminencie,</hi> that burying their <hi>honestie</hi> in its <hi>ruine,</hi> there will sca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ce be left them as much as to swear by.</p>
                  <p>And withall the <hi>Black Doctor</hi> sayes, <hi>he could, were it not for fear to give Offence to their Relations, name a Counter-list of these that have died under Dr. Brown's new method.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Thanks to Dr. <hi>Black</hi> for his tenderness, after he has <hi>Glutted</hi> himself with all <hi>Malicious</hi> and vile <hi>Calumnies,</hi> and <hi>Reproaches,</hi> wherein Persons of Honour and good Credit were concerned and named. It seems now he has some remorse, and is in a fit of Tenderness, and stands at Offence, he that so frankly just now dealt about Injuries; and which is more at Offence from an unkown hand: when the Devil (Oh, I mean the Fox) begins to preach, have a care of the Lambs: <hi>Black</hi> is not so desperatly wicked, but he can put on a visage of Tenderness to serve a greater De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sign: but I think it were greater Tenderness, and more Dr. <hi>Black</hi>'s Interest too, by such a Counter-list to have alayed the grief raised in these, who have had their Friends dead under his Methods, upon their seing so much probability, they might have been Cured, if they had been treated by <hi>Dr. Brown's</hi> new Method, and that at a far greater Cost, than such a <hi>Ridiculous</hi> and <hi>Chimerical</hi> Tenderness: but the Truth is, any such List being not only Impossible to be given
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:174794:34"/>but there being since, several that can be added to the List of these Cured, after the New Method, they are for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced to Palliat &amp; smother the matter after this Ridiculous manner, and if it could be given, as the giving of it in this Case, could not easily offend any Man, so it would be a considerable Service to the World, and prove a more Solid and Convincing Evidence for the <hi>Club,</hi> than all they have either said, or can say: there pretended <hi>Chimerical</hi> Tenderness then, is not only Cruelty to the whole World, but, which none but the highest degree of Fools can be guilty of, Cruelty to themselves: and therefore whether they be not in this pretence, either Lyars, or Fools, or both, let the World Judge.</p>
                  <p>It's here to be Considered, that altho this Method of Curing Fevers has proven as yet so exceeding succesful, that praise to the <hi>Author</hi> of all Gifts and Discoveries, Dr. <hi>Brown,</hi> and others has for several years practised it so suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cesfully, that there has scarce any died under it: yet it can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be thought Infallible, or so sure that it will never mis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carry, for there may be such Complication of other Dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempers with the Fever, that sometimes may evacuat the Effect: yet I think we may say of it, as <hi>Donkers</hi> in the <hi>obs.</hi> 32, of his Book <hi>de febre Petechiali</hi> sayes of a Method very like this, which he used so very succesfully, that scarce any died under it, he thinks it will a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree to <hi>all Fevers,</hi> whether <hi>Epidemical</hi> or <hi>Malignant,</hi> which <hi>Testimony</hi> of his was most <hi>Learnedly</hi> Confuted by <hi>one</hi> of the <hi>Eminencies</hi> of the <hi>Club,</hi> who, upon hearing of it <hi>Magisterially</hi> said, he did not much regard the <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glish Physicians,</hi> who were one thing to day, and another to Morrow: while in the mean time this <hi>Donkers</hi> is a <hi>German,</hi> and a <hi>Physician</hi> a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <hi>Cologne</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And albeit the <hi>Cardinal Point</hi> of this Method of Dr. <hi>Sydenhams</hi> be Purging, yet its folly to think, but there
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:174794:34"/>is great Art, and Dexterity to be used in the management thereof, the Quantity, Quality, the Time, and Repe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tition of the Purgative, which being used either within, or without the due bounds, and measure, proves alwayes useless or noxious.</p>
                  <p>So that the <hi>Objection</hi> of the <hi>Grand Club,</hi> that every <hi>Apothecaries Boy</hi> knows to do it, is <hi>Frivolous</hi> and <hi>Ignorant:</hi> yea, and if such a Method could be found out, that every <hi>Apothecary's Boy</hi> could use, it were a rich discovery: and therefore their Argument tells likewise, they are no ways of <hi>Generous</hi> or <hi>Publick Spirits,</hi> but <hi>Mean, Base</hi> and sel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fish <hi>Persons.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And now <hi>Philom,</hi> I think, I have run over the greatest part of their <hi>Learned</hi> mistaken <hi>Answer</hi> to my first Letter, (passing by the Pudle of disgorged Viper Spaun and fopred, for rakeing therein might raise steems very noxious to you) and shown that they have brought nothing against Dr. <hi>Brown,</hi> but plain <hi>Cavils, Calumnies,</hi> and <hi>Foppries,</hi> and indeed that which they Object in the last place concerning his Education, savours rank of their <hi>Innate Ignorance:</hi> for they suppose no Man can be tollera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly qualified, in <hi>Medicine,</hi> unless he be Bred at a forraign <hi>Ʋniversity.</hi> I pray you <hi>Club,</hi> what Universities were <hi>Hypocrates, Galen, Celsus,</hi> and many of the Antients bred at: and do you not know, that several of the most accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plisht <hi>Physicians</hi> in <hi>England</hi> were never out of their own Country, such as <hi>Sydenham, Willes,</hi> &amp;c. And that several of the most expert Lawyers in our own Nation studied at home. Pray, did you ever read <hi>Hypocrates</hi> his <hi>Lex,</hi> where he tells, that there are <hi>Nomine multi, re verà pauci medici:</hi> and he makes the chief condition, and means of Institution, to be Indu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ry and Education from a Child in the Practice. And indeed Dr. <hi>Brown</hi> being Educat in that Studie, and Practice from his Child-hood near 30
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:174794:35"/>
                     <hi>Years</hi> time, there is no body will doubt, but this <hi>caeteri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> paribus</hi> might be as good a mean for his acomplishment in a practice suitable to the <hi>genius</hi> of the <hi>Countrey,</hi> as thy breeding at a foraign <hi>university,</hi> for a short time would be.</p>
                  <p>As to what they object in further persuance of the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> Point concerning Dr. <hi>Brown</hi>'s receiving Degrees at <hi>Aber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deen</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>It's Answered, first, they receiving Degrees, in Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicine in any place, is very far from being a Testimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, or proof, of any Mans accomplishment: and is always given abroad <hi>periculo petentis,</hi> to the greatest <hi>Dunces</hi> that wil pay for it: And to prove this, can there be greater <hi>Blocks</hi> in the World than the <hi>Black Club</hi> (as their Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers do bear Witness) who are all Foraign <hi>Graduat Doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors;</hi> and has learned no thing abroad, but to Parat it to the Vulgar, after their return, in the <hi>Gibbrish</hi> of <hi>Jnsti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutions, Diss ctions, Courses</hi> of <hi>Chimistry, Colledges</hi> o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <hi>Medicine</hi> they learned abroad. and yet they never con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned the A, B, C. of true and solid Knowledge.</p>
                  <p>N<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>xt it's the greatest Impertinency Imaginable to dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parage Dr. <hi>Brown</hi> with receiving his Degrees at <hi>Aberdeen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi> where there is a <hi>Prof<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ssor</hi> of <hi>Medicine,</hi> for, besides that se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ral of the considerable Members of the Colledge of <hi>Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sicians</hi> at <hi>London,</hi> have received their Degrees there, can any <hi>Scots</hi> man doubt but the dignitie, or Honours flowing from the Soveraignity of our own Nation, are much prefer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to these Conferred by a <hi>Forraign,</hi> as is clear in <hi>Knight hood, Nobility,</hi> and who ever d sparaged a <hi>Doctor</hi> of <hi>Divinity,</hi> because he was Graduat within the Nation.</p>
                  <p>But with all (and it s em<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> the <hi>Blacks</hi> do not know so much, albeit they be must of them Members of this Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge) the Soveraignity of this Nation has by the Patent given to the <hi>Colledge of Physicians</hi> at <hi>Edinburgh,</hi> annex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed a Privilege to these Graduat within the Countrey be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:174794:35"/>any <hi>Graduat</hi> abroad; and that is, they are <hi>ipso facto</hi> free, and licentia<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> in the <hi>Colledge,</hi> without any <hi>Tryal</hi> or <hi>Composition;</hi> to all which these Graduat abroad are lyable▪ and what is this, but to hire us to be wise, and to incour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age domestick projects of Vertue, and Improvement, which these <hi>Blacks,</hi> as Enemies to Mankind in general, and to our National Improvement in Particular attempt to discourage and as the <hi>State</hi> has most justly given In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couragement to <hi>Domestick</hi> Graduation; So it were in my Opinion, the great happiness of the Nation, because, great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly tending to the Improvement of Medieine here, that Convenient Incouragement were given for the study, and Institution of <hi>Medicine</hi> within the Kingdom also; for thereby there would not only be saved a great deal of Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney that is Yearly spent in the Breeding of <hi>Physicians</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad; but also Students would be thereby better <hi>acom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plisht</hi> and <hi>Educat</hi> in the <hi>Practise</hi> suitable to the <hi>Complexi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> of the Nation, and <hi>Temper</hi> of the <hi>Climat;</hi> and the Deseases, and Cures proper to the <hi>Genius</hi> of the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try would become sooner familiar to them: for young <hi>Physicians</hi> bred abroad, return often very raw in <hi>Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cine,</hi> and alwayes quite strangers to the <hi>Genuine</hi> Practise of this Country.</p>
                  <p>And so <hi>Philom.</hi> every thinking Many may easily Collect, that the only proper expedient to redeem that Nation from these Inconveniencies, and to promote the Advantages above-mentioned, w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>re to Erect within the <hi>Kingdom</hi> a Profession of <hi>Medicine,</hi> with <hi>Hospitals</hi> for the Sick, sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>servient thereto.</p>
                  <p>And as Dr. <hi>Brown</hi> has done all in him lay to raise Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mestick Improvement and Vertue by his <hi>Graduation</hi> at home, so he has given a farther evidence of a publick <hi>Temper,</hi> by his being very Zealous to project that other National benefit of <hi>Domestick Improvement,</hi> the study in
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:174794:36"/>Medicine also at home: for he did not only prudently choice such a Patron to his Book, who (himself, and his Son having a considerable post in the State) seemed qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lified to lend the Project a Lift: and to whom, as <hi>Patron</hi> he might have more freedom, and access to represent, or negotiat it: but also he gave in to his Lo. a scheme of the Project in Writ, mentioning withal the retrival of (as Dr. <hi>Brown</hi> judges) Ane apposite Fond to sustain the Charge thereof; and as his very generous <hi>Maecenas</hi> at that time was pleased to look upon the Overture, as not altogether contemptible: so it's not to be doubted, but after more ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture deliberation, his Lo. will in that affair discharge the Office of a true <hi>Patriot</hi> of his <hi>Countrey.</hi> And this Passage <hi>I</hi> mention <hi>Philomath,</hi> not only as directly falling in my way, but more especially, because Dr. <hi>Brwn</hi>'s Enemies have been so Impudent, as to traduce his Temper, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>signs, and Mis<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>represent him strangely, also in these; but now a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>eal to all the World, if ever any <hi>Physician</hi> in the Nation, (not to speak of that Degenerous can Malicious Crew his Enemies,) gave such Testimony of Publick spiritedness, as this one passage (not to mention any more) clearly Imports he has done.</p>
                  <p>To return to our Purpose <hi>Philom,</hi> and to touch the <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finition</hi> of a <hi>Fever,</hi> which the <hi>Black Club</hi> desiderat in Dr. <hi>Brown</hi>'s Book: They essay to give none themselves, as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing like Ignorant <hi>bunglers,</hi> far better in throwing down other Mens Work, than building themselves; but how <hi>nonsensesical</hi> a doubt is this: just as one that had read both the <hi>Blaek Doctors Pamphlets</hi> should ask for a Discription of the <hi>Black Doctor,</hi> for as he is therein drawn to the Life, an Ignorant Fop, and malicious Brate: So almost all Dr. <hi>Brown</hi>'s whole Book is spent in explaining the <hi>Nature</hi> and, <hi>Phoenomena</hi> of Fevers, whose varietie being <hi>Indefinte,</hi> accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the various <hi>Disposition</hi> of the <hi>Impellent</hi> and <hi>Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:174794:36"/>of the Motion,</hi> the various <hi>Disposition</hi> of the <hi>moveable Matter,</hi> weither <hi>Solid</hi> or <hi>Fluid,</hi> and of the <hi>Passages</hi> throw which the <hi>Motion</hi> is made: that variety, <hi>I</hi> say, cannot al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low us to have a <hi>clear Idea</hi> of there, be brought under such narrow bounds as <hi>a Definition:</hi> but is rather the Subject mater of a <hi>Scheme:</hi> which Dr. <hi>Brown</hi> has essayed to draw in his Book.</p>
                  <p>Tho the <hi>Sign</hi> of a <hi>Fever</hi> commonly called <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>athognomick</hi> be the <hi>frequency</hi> of the <hi>Pulse.</hi> yet in some that are un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>questionably <hi>Fevers,</hi> the <hi>Pulse</hi> is not frequent, which <hi>I</hi> suspect may be solved thus. Albeit the <hi>Blood circulat</hi> as slowly in these as it does where the <hi>Pulse</hi> is more <hi>fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent</hi> and <hi>Consequently</hi> the <hi>Contraction</hi> and <hi>Dilatation</hi> of the <hi>Arteries,</hi> are but of the same <hi>Extent,</hi> as when the <hi>Pulse</hi> is <hi>frequent,</hi> yet because the <hi>Velocitie</hi> and swiftness of the <hi>Contraction,</hi> and <hi>Dilatotion</hi> is also lesed; and they become <hi>Languishing</hi> and <hi>slow;</hi> there may be als much time spent in that lesser <hi>Contraction</hi> and <hi>Dilatation,</hi> and in <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sequence,</hi> the <hi>Pulse</hi> beat as seldom on the Touch, as it does in health, where it moves with it's due <hi>velocitie,</hi> and so here the <hi>Velocity</hi> of the <hi>Contraction</hi> and <hi>Dilatation</hi> seems lesed, as well as the <hi>extent,</hi> of them, In Consequence, I think this <hi>Discription</hi> of a <hi>Fever</hi> not Improper.</p>
                  <p>A <hi>Fever is an universal difficult Circulation of the blood and Humors, throw their gr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>sness, and obstruction of the Passages, having several</hi> Phenomena, <hi>as immediate effects, and others mediat from the efforts of the Impellent or first mover for redintegration of their motion, which is excited by the Impressions these Immediat effects make on the Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pellent, as frequency of the Pulse and other orgasmes.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>A <hi>Fever</hi> has no <hi>Pathognomick Sign omni,</hi> it has a <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>the gnomick Sign soli,</hi> that's a frequent <hi>Pulse:</hi> and where that is wanting, the present state of the <hi>Bloods Circulation</hi> is Collected from a <hi>Syndrome,</hi> or <hi>Concurse</hi> of Causes useing
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:174794:37"/>to produce that grosness of the Blood; the Cause of def<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficult <hi>Circulation;</hi> and from the presence of the usual <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comitants</hi> of such a <hi>Disposition,</hi> and from the other <hi>Phe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nomena</hi> that as <hi>Irrdiations</hi> and <hi>Beams</hi> are darted from suc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> a <hi>Disposition:</hi> all which are more largely held forth by Dr. <hi>Brown</hi> in his Book.</p>
                  <p>Now if an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> would be satisfied to have a description o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <hi>Dr, Black<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi> Nature from his <hi>Phenomena,</hi> if <hi>Ho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>race</hi> who certainly was no wayes prejudicated his <hi>Descrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> of the man may be trusted, take it as he gives it <hi>Lib<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi> 1, <hi>Saty,</hi> 4, <hi>Line,</hi> 81.</p>
                  <q>
                     <l>—Absentemqui rodit amicum,</l>
                     <l>Qui non defendit Alio Culpante: solutos</l>
                     <l>Qui captat risus hominum Famam{que} dicacis</l>
                     <l>Fingere qui non visa potest: Commissa tacere</l>
                     <l>Qui nequit: hic niger est, hunc tu Romane Caveto</l>
                  </q>
                  <p>Englished because perhaps the <hi>Blacks</hi> understand Latin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> als little as they doe Greek.</p>
                  <q>
                     <l>Who honest men reviles behind their Backs,</l>
                     <l>And ne're defends them, he dots on senselels Knacks</l>
                     <l>A publick Railer, loves to break a Jest;</l>
                     <l>And to be merry-andro at a Feast.</l>
                     <l>Tells all he hears, and adds a great deal more</l>
                     <l>Which ne'r were seen or ev'r heard before,</l>
                     <l>My Countrey men beware of Dr, Black</l>
                     <l>A Brutish crew, an Ignorant Devilish pack,</l>
                     <l>Ther snarling Barking tells they'r Black mouth'd Dogs,</l>
                     <l>Their Cavelling quirking tells they'r Ignorant Rogues.</l>
                  </q>
                  <p>who ever desires a short and easy way, that th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> meanest Capacity may know a <hi>Black</hi> by; take this.</p>
                  <q>
                     <l>Would you a Black clearly discern</l>
                     <l>If Dr, <hi>Brown</hi> but meet him,</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Black</hi> looks on him so cruel stern</l>
                     <l>As truely he would eat him.</l>
                  </q>
                  <pb n="45" facs="tcp:174794:37"/>
                  <p>And to confirme all take also <hi>Hipocrates</hi> the most wise <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>f all <hi>Phisicians</hi> his Sentiments, in his Book <hi>De Arte,</hi> Where he sayes whosoever endeavours with <hi>Artifice</hi> of <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ndiscreet</hi> and <hi>Dishonest</hi> words to disgrace and abuse the <hi>Discoveries</hi> and <hi>Inventions</hi> of others, neither Endeavors <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>o amend them, but traduces them before the <hi>Ʋnlearned,</hi> He seems incapable to be esteemed <hi>prudent,</hi> and betrayes his <hi>Malicious Nature</hi> and <hi>Ignorance.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>But least I be thought to leave this <hi>Malice riden Crew</hi> in Wrath, (their number as well as their Condition deserve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ng pitty) I think it better to take a charitable farewel, and to leave them with a wholesome and sound advice, provid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing they be capable to fellow it; and its a prescription of which if they can but get the right Ingredients, and make <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ight up, it will quickly Cure their <hi>Distempers</hi> and mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>eries especially their <hi>Ignorance.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Take of Limpid and smartest M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>nstruum of</hi> Natural Acuteness, <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>s much as ye can get the more the better</hi>
                     <note n="*" place="margin">That which cannot very easily penetrate the prelumina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries of Dr, <hi>Brouns</hi> Schedule, especially that paragraph in the first Section concerning Acute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness, is quite dull and naught.</note>
                     <hi>Impregnat this</hi> Menstruum <hi>with a sufficient quantity of</hi> the fix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed salt of <hi>true sence of the Physicians duty and</hi> obligation <hi>lying on</hi> him to accomplishment<note n="*" place="margin">Not the volaltie for that is naught, this Salt must be made after the manner prescrived in the first Sect; of Dr, <hi>Browns</hi> Schedule.</note>
                     <hi>then add unto this</hi> Menstruum, <hi>thus impregnat als much as will be proportionat to the quantity of the</hi> Menstruum <hi>of</hi> serious Industrie <hi>constant Labour and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quisitive search,</hi>
                     <note n="*" place="margin">These must be gathered and prepared after the manner in the 2d, <hi>Sect,</hi> of Dr, <hi>Browns</hi> Schedule.</note> then seal the vessel with the Hermetical Seal of the Phisicians sequestration from other <hi>Imployes</hi> or <hi>Diversions.</hi> And set it in the <hi>Balneo</hi> of <hi>Speculation,</hi> let the <hi>Balneum</hi> be still keeped warm with the <hi>Constant</hi> heat of serious and <hi>Intent</hi> Application of the mind till the <hi>Menstruum Extract</hi> a <hi>Tincture</hi> that looks <hi>Brown,</hi> if it
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:174794:38"/>look <hi>Black</hi> all is spoilled, it will be of a <hi>Corrosive Poisonous</hi> Nature: then <hi>Filter</hi> the <hi>Tinctur</hi> throw the <hi>Filter</hi> of dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent Observation and so ye will have an <hi>Excellent Elixir Philosophorum</hi> called <hi>Medicinal Prudence,</hi> which ye may <hi>Aromatize pro renata</hi> when ye come to use it with some <hi>Guttes</hi> or <hi>Craines</hi> of Personal <hi>Prudence</hi> to make it more <hi>Palatable</hi> and <hi>Passing.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The vertues of the <hi>Elixir Prudentioe medicoe.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>It Cures all <hi>Reeling megrim, Giddiness</hi> in <hi>Physicians,</hi> all <hi>Deliriums,</hi> and <hi>Ravings,</hi> yea <hi>Madness</hi> it felf, if it be not natural, or from bad <hi>Conformation</hi> of the Parts.</p>
                  <p>Its excellent to clear their <hi>sight,</hi> helping all faults of the eyes, especially <hi>Suffusions;</hi> yea, it Cures Infallibly that mos<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> dangerous and <hi>Epidemical</hi> Disease in <hi>Physicians,</hi> the <hi>Gutt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> Serena,</hi> where the Orgains seem <hi>Intainted</hi> and <hi>Sound t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi> the Spectators, yet there is nothing but <hi>Darkness</hi> and <hi>Blindness</hi> within.</p>
                  <p>It's good in all deseases from <hi>Venome</hi> and <hi>Viper spaun<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi> and <hi>Malignant</hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>umors, especially against their <hi>Paroxcism</hi> and <hi>Fermentations,</hi> when being stirred up, they cause ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cesive belshing out of poysonous Eructations, notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standing whereof, they are in hazard to burst the Body of the <hi>Patient,</hi> and obliges him still to be Clasped in <hi>Iron-Bands</hi> and <hi>Fetters,</hi> like a <hi>Malefactor.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>It's good against all <hi>Stupidity</hi> and <hi>Fopishness in phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sicans,</hi> cutting all <hi>Snotty viscuous humors,</hi> purges ou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> all Fopred that dulls their Brains.</p>
                  <p>It's good for all <hi>Rickityness, Dwarfing</hi> and <hi>Sitting</hi> o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> in <hi>Physicians,</hi> making them advance more in on year the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> tbey would otherwise do in Twenty, or Thirty.</p>
                  <p>It's good for overflowing of the <hi>Gall</hi> and <hi>Heart-burn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,</hi> for all <hi>Chollerick Deseases,</hi> the <hi>Black</hi> and <hi>Yello<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> Jaundice,</hi> which make all things appear wrong to th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>m.</p>
                  <p>It's good also for the <hi>Apetitus Caninus</hi> in <hi>Physicians,</hi> which makes them de<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ore six times a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s much Imployment
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:174794:38"/>as they are able to disgest or dispatch, which is a disease ordinarly incident to these that are <hi>Duarft,</hi> and <hi>sitten</hi> one in Medecine.</p>
                  <p>I should have also given them a cure for ther Malice and wickedness: but that seems to be a Devil that cannot be cast out without Fasting and Prayer, therefore <hi>I</hi> must leave it to the Church-men.</p>
               </div>
            </body>
            <back>
               <div type="publishers_advertisement">
                  <head>The Publishers Advertisement to the <hi>Reader.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>Whereas the <hi>Black Doctor</hi> sayes he will Answer Dr, <hi>Brown</hi> no more which if he doe not, and be als good as his Word, I'l swear that it's the first time that a <hi>Skittish</hi> Jade after being so touched in the Quick, did not both Fling and F—t. too.</p>
                  <p>If Dr, <hi>Black</hi>'s back be <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>alled</hi> with whipping and Smart I have an extraordinary <hi>Anodine Balsome</hi> of <hi>Consolation</hi> to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ive him and its this.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Desine Flere niger nondum pro viribus egit.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Dr. <hi>Brown,</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Solace</hi> thy self, weep not <hi>Poor Sorry Black;</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>For <hi>Brown</hi> has not yet open'd half his <hi>Pack.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               </div>
               <div type="errata">
                  <pb facs="tcp:174794:39"/>
                  <head>Errata.</head>
                  <p>P 13. l. 2. for side, r. sides 16. d. to.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>ibid.</hi> l. 13. &amp; 14. f. Iamalmostina r. <hi>I</hi> am almost in a</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>ibid.</hi> l. 19. for <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ameimust r. shame must</p>
                  <p>p. 15. l, 16. f. encounterfit r. counterfit</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>ibid.</hi> l. 25. for advaners r. advancers</p>
                  <p>p. 16. l. 8. f. fair r. farie</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>ibid.</hi> l. 23. for any r. many</p>
                  <p>p. 17. l, t. f. rae r. rake</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>ibid.</hi> l. 13. f. than r. as</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>ibid.</hi> l. 31. f. Crackhouse r. Crack-louse</p>
                  <p>p. 19. l. 12. f. but ekspecially r. especially</p>
                  <p>p. 20. l. 31. f. will r. wit</p>
                  <p>p. 21. l. 3. f. scapes r. Scrapes</p>
                  <p>p. 22. l. ult for clad. r. Called</p>
                  <p>p. 23. l. 5. for Concatnation. r. Concatenation</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>ibid.</hi> l. 15. f. Penomena. r. Phenomena</p>
                  <p>p. 24. l. 23. f. idone r. is done</p>
                  <p>p. 26. l. 13. for bur r. bar.</p>
                  <p>p. 27: l. 6, f. violne r. violence</p>
                  <p>p. 30. l. 25. f. Phaetoins r. Phaetons</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>ibid.</hi> l. 28. f. Centnre r. centre</p>
                  <p>p. 33. l. 22. f. sent. r. Scent.</p>
               </div>
            </back>
         </text>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <body>
               <div type="letter">
                  <pb n="1" facs="tcp:174794:40"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>A</hi> Third Letter written by <hi>Philander</hi> to his Friend in the Countrey <hi>Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lomathes,</hi> in Vindication of Dr. <hi>Broun,</hi> and the new Cure of Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers promoted by him, against the Cavills and Scruples that some yet intertain against it.</head>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>Dear Philomathes,</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>IN your last to me, you earnestly desire to know in what Credit the new Cure of Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers is among us here: and that since you hear several considerable Persons are sudden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>y snatcht away by Fevers, you would also know whether they were treated by the purging Method, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> not. In answer to your last Demand, be pleased to know, that these Persons whom you <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>me, and many more who died of Fevers here <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> late, were treated in the old manner, and not at <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> by the purging Method: However they died <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>cundum artem.</hi> And to your Demand, about
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:174794:41"/>the Credit of the new Cure here; although as far as I can learn, there is scarce any die<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> under the purging Method, which inclines a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> considering and indifferent Men to favour it, y<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> the <hi>Physicians</hi> here are not disposed to follow i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> alledging a great many frivolous Scruples agains<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> it, as in the Sequel I hope I shall make plain t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> you, and all thinking Men.</p>
                  <p>Since the emitting of the <hi>Looking-glass,</hi> where in not only the new Theory of Fevers seems to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> very much confirmed, but also wherein D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <hi>Brouns</hi> Enemies seem to be represented to the lif<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> albeit they appear to be frighted out of the scribling Humor: Yet some of them take <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> great liberty of privat Calumniating and D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tracting as ever, either appearing open and dow<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> right Enemies to him and the Method, or som<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times by more subtile Insinuations, pretendin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Friendship to the Method, yet they detra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> and derogat from the universal use thereo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> by alledging that it is a Cure only proper in som<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> cases, and in some Fevers, and that it is not sa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> in all continual Fevers, yet in the mean time, th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> do not define and explain the Kinds of Fevers and cases wherein they think this Cure may <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> used and in which they think it may not be use And so I think they do little better than these th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> do absolutely condemn it. I would therefore de<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>sire all such persons, either to forbear this ridi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culus
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:174794:41"/>Censure of the new Method, or to conde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scend upon the particular Cases and Fevers in which they think this Method may be only used, and withal to confirm the same by sufficient Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience: For how impertinent are they that en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour by such Cavilling and Quirking, to over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn a matter of Practice, founded upon the so<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lid Experience that others have of the Efficacy of this new Method, and which they themselves have never touched, but with the airy Notion of a Phantastical Brain: And I truely think such Reasonings are as ridiculous in this case, as it would be horrible, to see a Man standing before the mouth of a Cannon, reasoning Gun-powder out of its Force, until he were all blown to Peices. For it is very certain, that all these Chymerical Quirks and Cavills, that they bring against the new Method, can be evidently controll'd by the solid Experience of that most expert Practitio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner in Medecine Dr. <hi>Sydenhame,</hi> who for several years before his decease, practised this new me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thod most successfully in all kind of Fevers, even in these called Malignant: And at all times and seasons thereof, when the Patients Strength not being exhausted could bear it. As also, the same <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>hantastical Reasonings can be most solidly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>uted, by the sound Experience of several other Physicians in this place, as of Dr. <hi>Broun,</hi> who these six or seven years bygone, has cured all th
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:174794:42"/>Fevers that occurred to him, by this Method, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept one or two mentioned in his Book, &amp; among those that were cured by him in that space, hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> own Children have happily gone through this Course of this Cure above sixteen times, and some of their Fevers were very dangerous, and with violent Symptoms; And further, the Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count that <hi>Dr. Cumming,</hi> now Residenter in <hi>Dubline</hi> gave of the Efficacy, of this Cure, is very remarkable and convincing: and not to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cealed from the World. For this Physician being a person of unquestionable Integrity, did the la<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> Summer when he was in this place, say, that h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> admired of the Carriage of the Physicians her<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> about the new Cure of Fevers, for he could <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sert, that of three hundred Patients, sick of Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers, that he had in the Camp in <hi>Ireland</hi> and whom he treated by the purging Method, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> could not say that above Three of them died▪ And moreover, he said he valued that Practic<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> more, than all that he knew in Medicine besides and all this he declared to many persons, wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> heard the same, and do witness it.</p>
                  <p>There is another Objection commonly start<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> against this Method, and entertained by many, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> a great Scruple against it, and it is this: Although the purging Method of curing Fevers, may an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swer very wel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> in strong, and robust Bodies, w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> can easily bear it, yet it is scarce safe in delicat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="5" facs="tcp:174794:42"/>and weak Constitutions. This Objection must be like ways answered from Experience, which hath plainly evidenced, that Persons of the most ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der Complexions, can easily endure this Cure. To clear this, beside the many other Examples that can be given, there has fallen out lately a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>markable and convincing instance in a Patient of <hi>Dr. Brouns:</hi> This Patient being Mr. <hi>David Forbes</hi> Advocat his Wife, a Woman of a most ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der and delicat Temper, and who hath brought forth twelve Children, she not being above thir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty one years of Age, and who had also brought forth a Child about two Months before she took the Fever, and so that she was scarcely well reco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered of Child-bed; This Patient, notwithstand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the weakness of her Constitution, and weakness from her late Recovery from Child-bed, and of the greatest weakness that she was in through the violence of the Fever, which beside other dangerous Symptoms, was accompanied with a great starting of the Nerves, commonly so called; yet she was happily cured by the purging Method, and she was all along soundly purged in the Violence of the Fever, and the Purge re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peted four or five times, intermitting some days betwixt every Purge, until the Fever and all the Symptoms were purged off: And the effect of every days purging was very visible, for the next day after every Purge, she had ease, and so gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dually
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:174794:43"/>the Fever was worn off by the Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thod.</p>
                  <p>There seems to be another set of Detractors whose Humor and Envy does clearly betray their Ignorance, and these do detract from the Repu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of Doctor <hi>Sydenham,</hi> who was the first In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venter of this new Method: For they say it was long in use before Doctor <hi>Sydenham</hi> did write it; and so they conclude, if it be so good a Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thod, as its given out to be, it could not have worn out of use? To which it is Answered its true the curing of Fevers by Purging, was re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commended by <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>everal Authors before him, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> by <hi>Fernelius, Guido Patin</hi> and <hi>Sylvius Delebo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi> &amp;c. But by the Observation of the unluckie ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects that sometimes fell out, by the Tumult an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Commotion the Purgative raised in the Humors the purging in Fevers was for the most pa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> laid aside, until Doctor <hi>Sydenham,</hi> among man<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> other excellent Discoveries he found out in Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicine; fell upon the seasonable use of the <hi>Par<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gorick,</hi> or <hi>quieting Medicine,</hi> to be given after t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <hi>Operation</hi> of the <hi>Purge,</hi> for staying the <hi>Tumul<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi> and <hi>Commotion</hi> of the Humors raised in the Bod<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> by the <hi>Purgative;</hi> All which, with the rest of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Method of that Cure, is more fully explained <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> in Doctor <hi>Broun</hi>'s <hi>Vendicotorie Schedule.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>As to these personal <hi>slanders</hi> and calumnies th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Dr. <hi>Browns</hi> enemies make use of against him, and
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:174794:43"/>which are in their printed <hi>Dialogue:</hi> all conside<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring men may see how ridiculous these <hi>Physitians</hi> are, that bring false and malicious aspersions against Dr. <hi>Brown;</hi> for his promoting of this new Cure, which aspersions, although they were true, they can make nothing against the efficacy of that Cure. I shall touch at one aspersion in this <hi>Dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logue,</hi> which as it is a manifest and notorious un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truth; so all men may thereby guess what veri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty is in the rest of them, and that is <hi>pag.</hi> 36. where they represent him as a man hasting to be rich, and taking all indirect ways to get imploy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, by supplanting other <hi>Physitians,</hi> and scru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ing himself by unjust means into business, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as it is known, he is so little solicitous that way, that he is not at the pains to reside and attend at <hi>Edinburgh,</hi> but dwells for the most part in the Countrey, and several of his Friends have been very serious with him, telling him that he wronged his privat Fortune very much, which might have a considerable increase, by his fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing his Imployment in <hi>Edinburgh;</hi> and it is very well known, that oft-times Patients in <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinburgh,</hi> have called him out of the Countrey to <hi>Edinburgh</hi> to attend them there: as did Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>missar <hi>Scougal,</hi> who <hi>anno</hi> 1688. called him from the Countrey to <hi>Edinburgh</hi> to cure him of the Fever by this new method, which he was per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swaded was by far the best, as did likewise the
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:174794:44"/>Tutor of <hi>Gorthie,</hi> one of the Clerks to the Bills when the most part of his Family had the Fever<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> and whom he also happily cured by this purging method, and several others have in the like man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner called him, whom it is needless here to men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
                  <p>Neither seems Dr. <hi>Brown,</hi> or this new Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thod to be any better circumstantiat, with som<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> that appears to be his Friends and well wisher<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> who though they are convinced of the efficacy an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> vertue of this new cure; yet they dissemble an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> disguise much of that which they know of it, an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> that from a spirit of envy and jealousie, for the perceiving that this his essay to introduce such great benefit to the World, as a new and mo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> successful Cure of these dreadful Fevers (which hath been so formidable in many Families, in m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>king a sudden havock of the strongest men, an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> that in their full strength and vigour) is an a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tempt so great, that if he prove successful therein it may advance him to that high pitch of reputati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, as will not only dazle their envious eyes, and make them dispare of his being so useful and ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viceable to them as before; but withal may rai<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> the merit of his former services done to then higher than their detracting <hi>Genius</hi> can well en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure to behold it.</p>
                  <p>There is another Motive influencing some, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> specially younger <hi>Physitians,</hi> to suppress their per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swasions
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:174794:44"/>about this Cure, and that is a too servile veneration they carry to elder <hi>Physitians,</hi> and so that for fear of offending them, they are cow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed into an indifferency and coldness, in maintain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the effects or utility of this method.</p>
                  <p>In how fair an appearance to come in request was this new method, after the Master of <hi>Forbes</hi> was cured thereby, every body crying up the new Cure of Fevers, but what odd endeavours to blast that appearance were made by the strange behavi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our of one of his <hi>Physitians,</hi> who concurred with Dr. <hi>Brown</hi> in that Cure, I pray God that what he did in that matter be not laid to his charge in the great day of accompts.</p>
                  <p>Amongst the other difficulties that Dr. <hi>Brown</hi> hath met with in carrying on this design, for the publick good, in which, altho he laid his account with Gods assistance to encounter all the malicious opposition, self-seeking <hi>Physitians</hi> who feared a di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minution of their reputation by the coming in of any new improvement, could raise against him, yet he has not had the good fortune to have any great men for his patrons, to protect or encourage him under the malicious opposition he met with, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther has he many acquaintance, and familiars to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend him: Whereas on the contrary, his enemies are both a multitude, and have all their particular friends and acquaintances to stand by them; yea they have not only procured great men for their
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:174794:45"/>patrons, as witness their influencing a conside<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Statesman, to license their calumnious <hi>Dialogue</hi> printed against him; but they also attempted to have rivald him of the prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction and patronage that by the most sacred bond of trust was due to him. <hi>Verbum sapienti sat est Psal.</hi> 118. <hi>v.</hi> 8, 9. and 146 <hi>v.</hi> 3.</p>
                  <p>By all which <hi>Philomathes,</hi> you and all thinking men may see how much self, and sinister designs predomine over men, to the great hurt and dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>advantage of the publick good: and that any advance Dr. <hi>Brown</hi> has made, is not by men, but by the blessing of God alone upon his honest endeavours: Dr. <hi>Brown</hi> does then by all the Laws of honesty and virtue, obtest all ingenius men, whether <hi>Physitians</hi> or others, but especial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>Apothecaries,</hi> who have frequently seen the signal effects of this Method (and whom I could here name, but I think that they are such honest men, that they will not need a spur to their du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty) that at such a time, when the good of the World so much requires it, they do not draw back their assistance, and suffer themselves to be carried away by such mean and sinister designs, to the great prejudice of the publick interest, by smoothering what they have seen of the efficacy of this Method. For as their due owning of this Method might have before this time so fully brought it in request, that many who have pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rished
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:174794:45"/>for want of it, might have been saved; so it may justly be feared that their negligence and pusilanimity in this case, may be charged with the fatal and dismal consequences arising from <hi>Physi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tians</hi> slighting this Method, who, I think, durst not do it, if they had received such impartial ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counts of its vertue and power, as several per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons were capable to have given them, and so I hope no considering man will venture to serve his petty polliticks, by detracting, conniving, or jugling, in a matter of so universal import, but will reckon even their neglecting to own and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance it, while it is in their power to do it, a downright betraying of so great an Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rest.</p>
                  <p>Now it is to be remarked here, that in extol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling the vertue and efficacy of this Method, there is only mentioned what has been done: for God only knows if this method, or any other will al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways hold, for the future; Nay, no body can affirm, that the Cure of the <hi>Agues</hi> by the <hi>Jesuits</hi> bark, which is reckoned so great an improvement in Medicine, will always hold.</p>
                  <p>Yet these who have found the new Cure of Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers so successful, cannot in Conscience forsake, either the following it, or maintaining it, until it forsake them, and prove ineffectual: Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as on the other hand, I am certain there is none that disparages this Cure, but either those who do
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:174794:46"/>it for base and self ends, or these who never have seen it practised.</p>
                  <p>And it is withal to be remarked, that as there is great art and dexterity required in the practice of this method, especially in difficult and dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous cases, for it may miscarry in the hands of no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vices, or these that are unexperienced in it: so there is greater care and industry required in the managing of it than many, especially such as are already arrived to any degree of eminency in <hi>Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sick,</hi> are willing or capable to undergo, and this seems sufficient to startle all such as think they can maintain their reputation without medling with it.</p>
                  <p>And as Dr. <hi>Brown</hi> hath a firm perswasion, from certain and &amp; frequent experience of the utility and profit of this method, in all the cases he has met with as yet.</p>
                  <p>So he has out of a principle of Charity to all the World, been very careful to invite all other <hi>Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sitians</hi> to follow it, and has offered to severals that had scruples about it to clear them of their doubts, by shewing them the practice it self, when it occurred to him, but with few or none he could ever prevail to take notice of it, though he himself when he heard of this Cure first, was so solicitous about it, to be convinced of it, he went expresly to <hi>London</hi> to see Dr. <hi>Sydenhame</hi> pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctise it.</p>
                  <pb n="13" facs="tcp:174794:46"/>
                  <p>To make this method the more plausable, to men of delicate and Scholastick tempers, Dr. <hi>Brown</hi> has in his <hi>Vindicatory Schedul,</hi> essayed to give so<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lid grounds for it, from sound Reason, and this founded upon a more clear <hi>Scheme</hi> of Fevers also offered by him to the World, than any I appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend has appeared as yet: all which he has sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jected to the cosideration of the ingenious, and faithful <hi>Physitians:</hi> But as if there were none such in this part of the World, he has received little or no answer from any such as yet, and now Dr. <hi>Brown</hi> does moreover a second time, invite all ingenious and faithful <hi>Physitians,</hi> who enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain sentiments different from his, either in rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to the Theory, or the practice of the Cure of the Fevers, that they would be pleased both for the Worlds greater satisfaction, and for further discovering in this dark subject, and the nature of Fevers, candidly to impart the same to him, who purposes, God willing to do his utmost endeavour to answer them in so weighty and concerning a point.</p>
                  <p>And for these that being seated in an <hi>eminency</hi> and <hi>Dictatorship</hi> in <hi>Medicine,</hi> shall from hence<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forth attempt to give peremtory <hi>Edicts</hi> in preju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dice of this new method, or shall be pleased for the future to take that unmannerly and unman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly way of detracting, corroding and gnawing of his sincere endeavours for the advancement of so
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:174794:47"/>great a publick Good, especially such as hav<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> been before approvers and commenders of this ne<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> method.</p>
                  <p>If the mild and healing means, of serious Dis<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>courses, and Intreaties by missive Letters, to for<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bear their calumnies, prove ineffectual, I hope no body will think that their eminencies are mal<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>treated, when they are levelled; and they, not<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>withstanding of all their other fair pretensions discover'd it to be the viperous Vermine &amp; Moth<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> of so comfortable an accession of benefit to men, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> this new Cure of Fevers seems to be, and there<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore none will judge that they are cruelly treated, but most justly dealt withal (as on<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> corrosive is oft-times an antidot to another) <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> they be soundly plyed home with more severe and smart <hi>Poyson-driving</hi> means then hath hitherto been ufed ugainst them, or that there be some <hi>Arsnick provided for these Rats, and that there be hue and cry sent after these Robbers, and Murde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers, A whip for the Horse, a bridle for the Ass, and a rod for the fools back,</hi> Prov. 26.3.</p>
                  <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:174794:48"/>
                  <p>THE EPILOGUE TO The Five <hi>Papers</hi> Lately past betwixt the Two PHYSICIANS Dr. <hi>O.</hi> and Dr. <hi>E.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Containing some Remarks, Pleasant and Profitable, concerning that Debate, And the Usefulness of VOMITING and PURGING in FEVERS.</p>
                  <p>BY <hi>AND. BROWN, M. D.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <q>
                     <hi>Victrix causa Diis placuit, sed victa</hi>
                     <bibl>Catoni.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <p>
                     <hi>EDINBURGH, Printed by</hi> John Reid, <hi>Anno DOM.</hi> 1699</p>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div type="epilogue">
                  <pb facs="tcp:174794:49"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:174794:49"/>
                  <head>THE EPILOGUE, &amp;c. OR, Some Remarks on the late Debate about the Usefulness of VOMIT<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ING in <hi>FEVERS.</hi> &amp;c.</head>
                  <p>THO I have been much solicited, to shew my Opinion, about the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bate betwixt the two <hi>Physicians,</hi> concerning <hi>Vomiting in Fevers,</hi> in regard of its Affinity with the Practise of <hi>Purging in Fevers,</hi> which was mantain'd by me some years agoe, and vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lently oppos'd by a certain <hi>Club</hi> of <hi>Physici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans;</hi> I yet delay'd to give my Sentiments therein, until I should see whether the <hi>Learn'd Colledge</hi> of <hi>Physicians</hi> would inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose therein, and what would be their De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cision and Suffrage: For the Eyes of all Men were upon them, expecting that they
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:174794:50"/>would do something in it, whose Province it is, either to compesce or determine such Differences among their own Members, that the World might receive Satisfaction in these Controversies, which concern out Lives and Health; But whether they con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sider not that it belongs to them, or that they know not what to do therein, I am ignorant: For there is neither any thing done that way, nor intended so far as I can learn: Thus in the great Concern of Life and Health, every one is left to his own Capricious Opinion, at Hap-hazard, to take up with what he pleases, without be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ng beholden to them for Light and Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ection in such important and intricat Concerns, what to follow or what not: As whether or not a Patient that has been made Vomit only with Whey, may be said to have been vomited by a <hi>Physician,</hi> and the Direction ought to be found upon the <hi>Apothecarie's File;</hi> and whether a Vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miter being given by a <hi>Physician</hi> in a <hi>Fever,</hi> and the <hi>Apothecarie's File</hi> refer'd to; One would think it had rather been an <hi>Antimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nial Vomit,</hi> than a Vomit of Whey. And whether after twice Vomiting of a Patient
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:174794:50"/>with Whey, and purging him with two lenient Potions, and two Clysters, may one Ounce of <hi>Vomiting Wine,</hi> with three <hi>drams</hi> of <hi>Syrup</hi> of <hi>Buckthorn</hi> be given the <hi>9th</hi> day of a <hi>Fever?</hi> Or whether there be al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes as much hazard in <hi>Plentiful Purging,</hi> as Bystanders apprehend, who never were acquainted with the <hi>Purging Metbod in Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers?</hi> And whether or not by the vain Fears of Friends and By-standers, a Faithful and Expert <hi>Physician</hi> may be blunder'd, and a good Method disgrac'd? And whether dal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lying and triffling with a <hi>Fever,</hi> tho less ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptionable, be not more dangerous, and often of more fatal consequence, than <hi>Plen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiful Purging?</hi> And whither upon any ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>travagant Purging, the <hi>Quieting Medicine</hi> being a ready Remedy, since in the contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted Case it was not given till the <hi>Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary</hi>'s return to the <hi>Patient;</hi> May it be thought there was no need of it before that time?</p>
                  <p>These I take to be the most material Points in this Debate, which seems to be handled with a little more Heat and Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour, than is consistent either with the Import of the Matter, or Dignity of the
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:174794:51"/>Members of so Judicious a <hi>Society,</hi> who would be expected to treat all their Matters, and seek to advance the Improvement of Medicine, in Candor, Amity, and Peace.</p>
                  <p>Now, if I may lawfully interpose my Sentiments in these Matters, since the same has such Relation to the Debate about <hi>Purg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in Fevers,</hi> wherein the rest of the <hi>Physi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cians</hi> being concerned either as immediat <hi>Actors, Inciters,</hi> or <hi>Connivers,</hi> so exercised me that there passed betwixt us no fewer than eight Pieces in Print: Which termi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nat in another Sub-division of the <hi>Colledge</hi> it self, whereby they are now split into two halfs and parties, into <hi>Guelphs</hi> and <hi>Gibellins,</hi> which Rent still continuing, has of late broken out into this new Debate, where<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>upon there has passed five Peeces.</p>
                  <p>However others may think of all this my humble Opinion in the first place is, That this last Contest has made so plain profitable, and pleasant a Discovery, that it may attone for the Scandal of all the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer <hi>Divisions, Animosities.</hi> and <hi>Ruptures</hi> O blessed <hi>Breach,</hi> and happy and fortunate <hi>Rent!</hi> that has brought forth so much Light to <hi>Medicine,</hi> that does so far approve of the
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:174794:51"/>
                     <hi>Usefulness of Purging in Fevers,</hi> as to allow of <hi>Vomiting</hi> therein also, as may be seen in the Papers on both sides; And as <hi>ex malis moribus oriuntur bonae leges, Ill manners beget good Laws; So</hi> we may see <hi>Debates, Divisi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons,</hi> and <hi>Differences</hi> may bring profitable Things to Light, which would have been otherwise hid: As <hi>Sampson</hi> kill'd more <hi>Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>listines</hi> at his Death, than in all his Life; So it may be hop'd that this <hi>Division</hi> and <hi>Debate</hi> may occasion the killing of more <hi>Fevers</hi> than their Concord either ever did, or in appearance would have done. And as the best Antidote for the Venom of the <hi>Viper</hi> is the <hi>Viper</hi>'s flesh, so it is hop'd this wound may prove the true Cure of the vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ulent opposition this way of treating of <hi>Fevers</hi> has formerly met with.</p>
                  <p>And who would not rejoice to see such clear Light arise in Our <hi>Horizon</hi> of <hi>Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cine,</hi> as to behold the Credit and Authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of the <hi>Sagacious Dr: Sydenham,</hi> avouched and mantained, and his Judgement and Candor in his Writtings fully asserted by both Parties: And especially his method of Treating <hi>Fevers by purging,</hi> which had been too long and too much opposed by ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:174794:52"/>in this place, to the unspeakable loss of <hi>Medicine,</hi> and <hi>Detriment of Mankind.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And tho <hi>Dr, Sydenham</hi> in his last work his <hi>Schedula monitoria,</hi> only appoints purg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in <hi>Fevers,</hi> and does not go the length of <hi>Vomiting.</hi> Those disputants seem so <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> to approve thereof, that both of them al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low of giving <hi>Vomits▪</hi> in some cases also for which the Authority's brought by the One, seem to be needless, since it is n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> denied by the other party; But since the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> Authorities may make the Reader appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend that the <hi>Purging</hi> in <hi>Fevers,</hi> is no n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> Method and Practice: and that it was <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> use before Dr. <hi>Sydenhams</hi> time. It is to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> remarked, that <hi>Purging</hi> and <hi>Vomiting</hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <hi>Fevers,</hi> were used only now &amp; then befo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> his time, and as some Indications did R<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>quire, but were not used generally, or in grea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> and dangerous <hi>Fevers,</hi> because the Commo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tion oft times raised by the Operation <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> the <hi>Purgative</hi> or <hi>Vomitive,</hi> did frequent<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Exasperat the <hi>Fever,</hi> which made the <hi>Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sician</hi> often times Repent his use thereof And so Purging and <hi>Vomiting,</hi> was who laid aside with us, and the Cure Commite to <hi>Cooling ptisans, Emulsions, Clysters, Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dial,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:174794:52"/>Juleps, &amp;c.</hi> And that oft times with as litle Reason as Success: For the D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ease going to a <hi>Crisis,</hi> the Patients Life was alwayes in hazard, because in every <hi>Crisis,</hi> Nature stands as it were Hovering and <hi>In suspense,</hi> as it were with an equal Bal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lance, indifferent to Life or Death, which may be casten as with a grain, and he that suffers the Disease to go to a <hi>Crisis,</hi> does just as if he would throw the Dice upon his Patients Life: Whereas Dr: <hi>Sydenham</hi> considered that the Evacuation of the <hi>Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bifick Matter,</hi> did profitably intercept the <hi>Crisis,</hi> and was the thing indicated and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired in the Cure of <hi>Fevers,</hi> and that it <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ould be done by <hi>Purging</hi> &amp; that any Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>motion raised by the Operation of the <hi>Purge</hi> might be Commodiously allayed, by giv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the <hi>Paregorick, Pacisick,</hi> or <hi>Quieting Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicine,</hi> and thus the <hi>Morbifique</hi> matter, might be <hi>Evacuated,</hi> and a <hi>Hazardous Crisis,</hi> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitably prevented, without any Superveen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Commotion, or the Exasperating the <hi>Fever,</hi> whereby the Patient had the direct Benefit of the <hi>Purging,</hi> without the acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dental and Noxious effect thereof.</p>
                  <p>And as there are two wayes of these <hi>Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers,</hi>
                     <pb n="10" facs="tcp:174794:53"/>so there are two several wayes of prac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tising of this <hi>Method,</hi> for sometime these <hi>Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers</hi> are more <hi>Slow, Long,</hi> and <hi>Chronical</hi> in their Motion and progress; And some times they are more <hi>Rapid, quick</hi> and <hi>Peracute,</hi> and come quickly to an end either to <hi>Health or Death;</hi> In the <hi>Slow</hi> and <hi>Long Fever.</hi> Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle <hi>Purges</hi> Repeated at intervals are most Convenient, and there the quieting Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cine is Scarce needed: but in the quick and <hi>Peracute Fevers,</hi> sharpe <hi>Purges</hi> and <hi>Vomiters</hi> which work speedily, must without delay be given: For the <hi>Slow</hi> and <hi>Lenitive Method,</hi> in a <hi>Peracute</hi> and <hi>quick Fever,</hi> never stops its <hi>Course</hi> nor obviats its <hi>Carrier:</hi> And as this seems most reasonable and suitable to Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience, so it is very consorm to the Pract<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ise of an Eminent <hi>Author</hi> Dr. <hi>Panthot Presi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent</hi> of the <hi>Colledge</hi> at <hi>Lions,</hi> who in a Book lately emitted by him, shews that as the fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent use of <hi>Cordials,</hi> in <hi>Fevers</hi> is very hurt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, because moving the <hi>Humours</hi> with a fret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful <hi>Agitation,</hi> they Drive them to the head. So he used only <hi>Bleeding</hi> and frequent <hi>Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatives</hi> with <hi>a Laxative Ptisan</hi> taken seve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral times a day, without delaying <hi>Purging</hi> as <hi>Hippocrates teaches,</hi> to the end of the <hi>Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver:</hi>
                     <pb n="11" facs="tcp:174794:53"/>And if <hi>Dosings, Ravings, Convulsions</hi> or any other Frightful Symptoms did arise, then <hi>instantly,</hi> and without <hi>Hesitation,</hi> he appoints <hi>Emetique Wine</hi> to be given, than which he knows not a better Remedy. And there is an Abstract of his Book to be seen in the <hi>Miscellany Letters of the works of the Learned</hi> Emitted at <hi>London May</hi> 1695.</p>
                  <p>Now as to the controverted case betwixt the two <hi>Disputants.</hi> If, <hi>Dr: O:</hi> when he came to the Patient, who was treated be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore only with gentle <hi>Purgatives,</hi> and found him under any pressing <hi>Symptoms,</hi> and the <hi>Fever</hi> growing, I humbly suppose he did not amiss, to give <hi>Emetique Wine,</hi> and in such <hi>a dose</hi> as the Patient cou'd bear. And to say the truth, the <hi>doses</hi> of <hi>Emetique Wine</hi> are very various, according to the Disposition of Patients, and their Easiness to be moved, some taking two ounces for <hi>a dose,</hi> and other only two drams.</p>
                  <p>And considering that upon any exorbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant effect of the <hi>Purgative</hi> or <hi>Vomitive,</hi> the <hi>Pacifique</hi> or <hi>Quieting Medicine</hi> is instantly to be given, and in regard in this case, it was not given till the <hi>Ordinaries</hi> return, we may construct in Charity that there was no need
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:174794:54"/>there o before, and the Bystanders and Friends their apprehensions and fears about the patient might be groundless, they never having seen any in a <hi>Fever</hi> treated so, for the <hi>Purging</hi> method in <hi>Fevers</hi> had always been <hi>Disguised</hi> and <hi>couched</hi> by <hi>Physicians</hi> and the Bystanders keept always in igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance about it▪ (As witness somes calling the effect of a <hi>Purgative</hi> quietly given, a Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural looseness which would carry off the <hi>Disease,</hi>) &amp; if these Fears were improven by <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ny upon sinistrous designs, they could not do a more wicked thing, that being the way <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>o fright timorous People from the use of this profi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>able practise of purging in <hi>Fevers.</hi> And both Reason and Experience will shew to these that are acquainted with this way of Cure, that theres more Danger oft times in the neglect of plentiful <hi>Evacuations,</hi> than by the use of them, But as 'tis not good to overact a Cure, so it is not safe to Dally and triffle away time, which is sometimes very Precious, <hi>Occasio praeceps, Oportunity Slips</hi> and <hi>Medio Tutissimus ibis, the midle way is the Safest,</hi> But in my humble opinion a Patient that survived so great and so Plenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful <hi>Evacuations,</hi> would not probably have
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:174794:54"/>been cured without pretty considerable ones, and some more they <hi>Dalling</hi> and <hi>Triffling</hi> or <hi>Couching</hi> and <hi>Dissembling</hi> the method. But since our Disputants seem to be agreed about the substantials of this way of treating <hi>Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers</hi> by <hi>Purging</hi> and <hi>Vomiting,</hi> Pray let them not <hi>squable</hi> about the Circumstantials, and let them strive to out do on another in Effectual and Speedy Curing, without either over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>acting the Method, or shooting short of it: And I can tell them from Experience, that its hard to be believed, how great <hi>Evacuations</hi> in many cases are not only to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lerable, but also required in the Cure of <hi>Fevers,</hi> which we may the more freely ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture upon, having the <hi>Quieting Medicine</hi> alwayes at hand, to check any Exorbitan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy that way.</p>
                  <p>But by the by, it may be observed how pretty Divertising it is, notwithstanding the great Opposition made to this way of curing <hi>Fevers,</hi> to behold the Reception it now has, and to see persons at such Vari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance, yet substantially agree in this Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice, which is indeed no small Argument for it, like the <hi>Jews</hi> and <hi>Christians,</hi> who both agree to the Authority of the Old
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:174794:55"/>Testament: And if we narrowly observe several <hi>Physicians</hi> Practice, we will see some may be catched stealing into this Practise, and some too Cavalierly marching into it, some like <hi>Firrets</hi> and <hi>Moles</hi> working under Ground, and some frolicking and vapour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it.</p>
                  <p>As it has been the Fate of all new disco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veries, and Discoverers, to meet with op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>position, and Contradiction, witness the opposition made to the Circulation of the Blood, and the Cure of <hi>Agues</hi> by the <hi>Jesuits</hi> Bark. no wonder this improvement of thus treating <hi>Fevers,</hi> should meet with the same Lot, especially when it Receded so much from the common Road, which treated them only with <hi>Cooling Ptisans, Emulsions, Clys<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, Cordial Juleps, &amp;c.</hi> But when ever such improvments come to take place, <hi>Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sicians</hi> either Jugle or Labour to Disguise them, or with more Resolution than Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son, strives who shall be fore-most therein, and extend them farthest, as was done with the <hi>Jesuits Bark,</hi> which was not only rash<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly used in all continual <hi>Fevers,</hi> but by some most Proposterously, to the Cure of most Diseases.</p>
                  <pb n="15" facs="tcp:174794:55"/>
                  <p>I hope then it will not be unpleasing, that I offer my humble Sentiments, in Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation to the Solution of this <hi>Moral Phaeno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menon,</hi> these strange appearances of the Actions of Men, in their <hi>Opposing, Shifting,</hi> or <hi>Streaching</hi> things at this Rate, to the great Detriment of <hi>Medicine</hi> in particular, and of Mankind in general.</p>
                  <p>In regard new <hi>Discoveries</hi> in <hi>Medicine</hi> ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear not at first to every one so plain and clear. as to silence <hi>Contradiction▪</hi> they are sure to meet with opposition from the weak and less <hi>Perspicacious,</hi> and with <hi>Quible,</hi> and <hi>Cavil</hi> from a Spirit of Detraction in Elder <hi>Physicians,</hi> who are Jealous that new improv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment <hi>Derogate</hi> from them, or their <hi>Experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence,</hi> or that they are in hazard thereby to be reduced to the same level with young<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er <hi>Physicians,</hi> and be put to go to School a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain to learn a new, and with all they <hi>a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bominate</hi> any thing that may be in hazard to convict their former practise of Error or mistake; Tho such an error seems Venial untill the occasion of delivery from it ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear, but the Mischief is, that the pride of Self-seeking Men is such, that before they will Acknowledge the least Bleemish or In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmity
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:174794:56"/>they will run the hazard of being the greatest <hi>Criminals</hi> Under Covert, not only by the Mischief they do by their own Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt of such <hi>Practical Improvments</hi> but by their Example and Authority, drawing many younger <hi>Physicians</hi> after them, some following them out of <hi>Reverence,</hi> and others out of <hi>Fear.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>But for the more full clearing this Matter, it would be considered, That as all Men may be divided into these four sorts, so <hi>Physicians</hi> are likewise divisible in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to as many kinds — The first sort are of these who have a great Stock of <hi>Sense</hi> and <hi>Learning;</hi> And withal, no less <hi>Ingenui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty</hi> and <hi>Candor.</hi> The second sort are these who have much <hi>Ingenuity</hi> and <hi>Honesty,</hi> but little <hi>Sense</hi> and <hi>Learning.</hi> The third sort are these who have much <hi>Sense,</hi> &amp;c. but little <hi>Candor</hi> and <hi>Ingenuity.</hi> The fourth are these who have little <hi>Learning</hi> and <hi>Sense,</hi> and as little <hi>Ingenuity</hi> and <hi>Candor.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>For the first sort, as they will quickly discern, take up, and follow new Improve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, they will as readily own, maintain, and endeavour to propagate them.</p>
                  <p>For the second sort, tho they be long in
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:174794:56"/>discovering such <hi>Improvements,</hi> yet their <hi>Honesty</hi> makes them <hi>Modest</hi> and <hi>Doubtful,</hi> &amp; keeps them from opposing them, waiting until their weakness comprehend them.</p>
                  <p>For the third sort, tho they quickly dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern such <hi>Improvements,</hi> yet for <hi>By respects,</hi> and <hi>Sinister Ends,</hi> they are shy in falling in with them, or if they do it, they <hi>Jugle</hi> and <hi>Dissemble</hi> the Use of them, and labour to <hi>disguise</hi> them, in so much, that by their hidden and reserved following them, they are so straitned, that they never come to any Perfection in them.</p>
                  <p>For the fourth sort, as they are slow in taking them up, so they are long in own<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them, after they take them up, and as they are the most constant, so they are the most violent Opposers of them, and always until it be a Scandal so to do, their Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment taking as much time to be Convinced, as their Honesty to be engaged to own or Defend them.</p>
                  <p>And I may say of these two last Sorts, if they shall also be Cursed with any conside<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Degree of Credit or Reputation, to plague the World, and to hinder the Good of Mankind, by the propagation of such an
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:174794:57"/>Improvement as this. <hi>(for Fortune never be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stows her Gifts so blindly as upon Physicians)</hi> When ever such come to discern and follow it, unless they be past feeling, and have their Consciences wholly Secred, they will be affected with a Torture and Remorse, proportionable to their guilt, and their ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cession to so many Deaths, as has been caused thorow their contempt of this <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thod,</hi> and that not only within the Verge of their own practice, but also within the Sphere of Activity of their Credit and <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority,</hi> which may perhaps be no small precinct to some, it being very plain that he that neglects the right way to cure his Patient, while it is in the power of Art to help him, is as guilty as he that direct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly maletreats him unto death.</p>
                  <p>And there is no <hi>Physician</hi> who rightly understands the import, weight, and intri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cacy of his Employment, and the great Charge lying on him to be accomplisht therein, so far as is possible for Study, Enqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry and Search to go, who will leave any stone unturned, to find out a more effec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual cure of <hi>Fevers,</hi> than that which has been commonly used, by <hi>Bleeding, Cooling
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:174794:57"/>Ptisans, Emulsions, Clysters, Cordial Juleps, &amp;c.</hi> which every <hi>Apothecarys</hi> Boy can by Rote tell, as perfectly as the Physician himself; And which can be made evident to do more hurt than good, beside the loss of time spent upon such triffling.</p>
                  <p>Now if every <hi>Physician</hi> would be pleased to Examine himself, and consider what his behaviour has been, in Relation to this <hi>Improvement,</hi> he may thereby know what place he may take in the foresaid <hi>Scale,</hi> for according to his <hi>Approbation</hi> or <hi>Opposition</hi> of this <hi>Improvement,</hi> his <hi>Jugling, Shuffling</hi> or <hi>Plain dealing</hi> therein, he must necessarly be ranked; But all Men may see, what place our two Disputants have, who not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withstanding of their Animosity and diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence, do both in their practice and Writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, own and maintain Dr. <hi>Sydenham</hi> and his <hi>Writings,</hi> wherein he delivers this way of <hi>Treating Fevers,</hi> and they being of two different parties, <hi>Guelphs</hi> and <hi>Gibellins,</hi> we may also guess at the Sentiments of their Respective Associats.</p>
                  <p>So it is hoped now, no Physician in this place will any longer <hi>Bogle</hi> or <hi>Scar</hi> at this way of Treating <hi>Fevers,</hi> or <hi>Shuffle,
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:174794:58"/>Jugle,</hi> or <hi>Dissemble</hi> it, to the scandal of their Profession, the straitning of them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves, and the marring of their own and others accomplishment in this practice, For I am certainly informed, that the <hi>Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thecaries</hi> begin to practise it, with the greatest <hi>Freedom</hi> and <hi>Success;</hi> And One of them told me, that he has not only seen many others cured that way, but that al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>so he himself was Cured of a most des<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perate <hi>Fever,</hi> by <hi>Purging:</hi> And that he was happily treated that way, by the Joint Advice of the <hi>Physicians</hi> who waited on him, and that at that time-few <hi>Physicians</hi> approved of, or publickly owned that way.</p>
                  <p>And tho as both our <hi>Disputants</hi> remark, Dr. <hi>Sydenham</hi> in his last work, the <hi>Monitory Schedule,</hi> only says, This Method is prefer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to all others in very many kinds of <hi>Fevers,</hi> yet thereafter he told to my self, and to several others, that he doubted not, but it would agree with all <hi>continual Fevers,</hi> tho he did not think fit, to publish all that he thought of it, because it might dero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gat from some of his former Writings, and he judged it would never be left off, when once it came in use, because he doubted
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:174794:58"/>not but it would be alwayes more succesful <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>han any other way, and thorow all <hi>consti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutions</hi> of years, and as he had practised it se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral years before the last Edition of the <hi>Schedula</hi> 1687; so I have practised <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> with the greatest success ever since, being <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> years: and a Cure that has holden so ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny years, it is not to be doubted but it will hold good alwayes, tho in difficult and dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous Cases, it requires great <hi>Care, Dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence</hi> and <hi>Caution,</hi> and <hi>Dexterity</hi> therein, an only be acquired by <hi>exact Attention</hi> and <hi>Consideration,</hi> and due <hi>Experience;</hi> and this may be a Reason why some Physicians are unwilling to take up with it, as being averse to give the Attendance sometimes requisite in this <hi>Cure,</hi> and these who want Experience therein, can only bungle at it, and know not how to go thorow with it; for in difficult and dangerous Cases, like the Management of a Ship in a Storm, where the Master must not only always be at the <hi>Helm,</hi> but also be well acquainted with the way he ought to take; So it re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires not only the <hi>Physician</hi> to be close at his <hi>Post,</hi> but likewise to be no Strang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er to the Way he ought to take. And
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:174794:59"/>especially in the Fevers that reign at this time, which are most part <hi>Quick</hi> and <hi>peracute,</hi> and cut off in a few dayes persons of impure Bodies: And as I have used this Method by <hi>Vomiting</hi> and <hi>Purging</hi> in many, and most successfully, at this time, so I have had lately considerable Experience thereof in my own Family, <hi>Wherein Four of my Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren and Ten Servants had the Fever, and blessed be GOD, all are Recovered;</hi> By repea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted <hi>Vomiting,</hi> with <hi>Antimonial Vomits,</hi> and frequent <hi>Purgings;</hi> Except two Servant<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> the one having gotten a great Stress <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> work, who bragging of his strength, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> contend with his Neighbour at the <hi>Mowi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi> of Hay, and presently sickned, and di<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> the <hi>sixth</hi> day, and whom I saw not at the day before he dyed, and found him <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> such a condition, that I could not give him either <hi>Vomite</hi> or <hi>Purge;</hi> and the othe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> was his Neighbour who strove with him being a Man of a most <hi>Impure</hi> and <hi>Emacia<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi> Body, who had endured want and Str<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> before he came to my Service, and who got not all was necessary, because he h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> not the occasion of due <hi>Attendance,</hi> a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> my Servants being sick at the time, And
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:174794:59"/>as both my <hi>Children</hi> and <hi>Servants</hi> that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covered, were <hi>Vomited</hi> several times with <hi>Antimonial Vomits,</hi> besides frequent <hi>Purg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,</hi> so it was astonishing to consider the quantity &amp; Corruption &amp; Virulency of the Matter <hi>Vomited</hi> up by them, and as I have in this matter sincerely told the Truth, which is also for the most part nottour in the place: So every one may judge how Malitious the Reports industriously spread abroad of me, Are, <hi>Viz.</hi> That seven of my Servants are lately Dead in <hi>Fevers,</hi> under this Cure, Whereas tho I have kept Servants near these Thirty years, Except these two, I had never any before that Dyed in my Service, tho the <hi>Fever</hi> has <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>everal times before been in my Family, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nd among my Servants and Children, I <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ope the Reader will not think this Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ression altogether impertinent, or out of Vanity, since it is both for my own Just <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nd Necessary Vindication, and the defence <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>f this profitable <hi>Practice.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Yea I hope I might be also allowed to say something now also by the by, about o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Calumnies and Slanders raised, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ropogate against me about the cure of
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:174794:60"/>the <hi>Gout,</hi> Especially by a certain <hi>Person</hi> who keeps a <hi>Publick-house,</hi> and whom I served most diligently, without any other Gratification, but Slander &amp; Back-biting, for the Errors committed most unreasonably by the Patient, and which slanders some <hi>Physicians</hi> also take pleasure to Trumpet a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad, tho many other <hi>Gentlemen</hi> may from their Experience testify the help I have given them in that Disease, if they please; And the <hi>Balsome</hi> I use, therein is the same with that used at <hi>London,</hi> &amp; aproven by 30 Members of the <hi>Colledge</hi> of <hi>Physician<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi> there. as has been frequently mentioned i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> the Gazette; But of this enough at thi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> time: Another time if there be any mo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> Reason for it, may do as well, and <hi>verb<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap> Sapienti sat est,</hi> a word is enough to a wis<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Man.</p>
                  <p>But to return to the purpose, it is further to be remarked that as Persons of <hi>impure</hi> Bodys and abounding with <hi>vitious humour<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi> are most subject to these <hi>Epidemical Fevers</hi> so they are in most peril thereby, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore all such Persons would be admonished that by the Advice an able <hi>Physician,</hi> i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> such an Epidemical time, they would ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="25" facs="tcp:174794:60"/>use of fit means for <hi>Prevention,</hi> whereby they may either escape the <hi>Fever,</hi> or if they be seised, it may thereby prove more <hi>Benigne</hi> and easily <hi>curable,</hi> and among all the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medys for Prevention, as well as for cure, I know none more effectual as is mention<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the Letter insert in Dr. Os. last peice than <hi>Antimonial Vomits,</hi> which notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standing the fear some People have of them, may be so ordered, that they will work with as much security and ease, as a <hi>Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gative Medicine,</hi> and such Vomits not only prepare▪ and open the way, for the more effectual operation of <hi>Purges,</hi> But also one <hi>Vomit</hi> has more effect, than two <hi>Purges;</hi> which is of considerable advantage in <hi>Pera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ute</hi> and <hi>quick Fevers,</hi> which still require a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>peedy remedy by <hi>Evacuation,</hi> and no <hi>alter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>tives</hi> or <hi>Correctors</hi> of <hi>vitious Humors,</hi> can <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>o suddenly <hi>restore,</hi> and <hi>alter</hi> such a corrupt <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ass</hi> of <hi>Humors,</hi> as are usually evacuat in <hi>Fevers</hi> by such <hi>Vomits.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Now considering this whole matter, the Opposition this practise has met with, and progress it has made, (the full and clear History whereof, may perhaps hereafter be published for satisfaction of the curious,) it
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:174794:61"/>is humbly proposed and referred to the seri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous consideration, of all Physicians, whether or not they ought to be very wary and ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der in their behaviour, about the <hi>Disco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veries, Inventions</hi> and <hi>Experiences</hi> of others, and whether or not they rather ought to inquire, ponder, and Modestly be informed about them, than be rashly driven by a spirit of <hi>Pride, Humour</hi> and <hi>Caprice,</hi> to run them down by all their power, and all Younger Physicians especially, would be exhorted to beware whom they take for <hi>Patrons</hi> and <hi>Examples,</hi> for <hi>ex quovis ligus non fit Mercurius,</hi> the best Stock of Natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Sense and Learning being little enough for a Foundation to make a competent <hi>Physician;</hi> and without it, tho they grow old in <hi>practise,</hi> they will never acquire true Skil and Real Experience in this difficult, intricate, and important <hi>Art,</hi> and Fame, and Reputation more rarely accompanyes real Merit in this Faculty and Function, than i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> any other whatsoever. The Vulgar upon whose noise <hi>Fame</hi> depends, being more com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petent <hi>Judges</hi> in any thing, than in the <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trigues</hi> of this hidden <hi>Art.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>If some younger Physicians shall be plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:174794:61"/>here to enquire, since they have not <hi>Experience</hi> themselves, and that they must <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ean to the <hi>Experience</hi> of Others, how shall they discern the Men of Real <hi>Experience,</hi> true Skil and <hi>Merit;</hi> and distinguish them from Men of meer <hi>Vogue</hi> and <hi>Fame:</hi> For the Satisfaction of such, and as a mean to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent their being initiated in the Errors and <hi>Mistakes</hi> of Others, which being once taken up, are not easily forgone. I hope I may be allowed to make a little Digression to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monish them, that they ought to be very cautious how they are led by the <hi>Dictates</hi> and <hi>Sentiments</hi> of these three or four sorts, whatever <hi>Vogue</hi> and <hi>Reputation</hi> they have. The first are these, who by driwing the <hi>Trade of Commeradship, Good Fellowship,</hi> and <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>on-Companionrie</hi> have gotten many Fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liars and Acquaintance who will cry them up for great Physicians, for all know how generally acceptable such Conversation is, and what a <hi>Noise</hi> so many Mouths well run'd up this way make.</p>
                  <p>The second <hi>Sort</hi> are, These who are <hi>High flowne</hi> or <hi>bigotted</hi> to a <hi>Party,</hi> either in <hi>Religion</hi> or <hi>State,</hi> and these who make more than an Ordinary <hi>Semblance</hi> and <hi>shew</hi>
                     <pb n="28" facs="tcp:174794:62"/>of <hi>Probity,</hi> whether <hi>Real,</hi> or <hi>Affected</hi> only I will not determine, but the Opinion of a <hi>Goodman,</hi> a <hi>Man</hi> of <hi>Probity</hi> or <hi>Integrity,</hi> tho they also know him to be a very <hi>weak man,</hi> goes a <hi>great way</hi> with the <hi>Vulgar</hi> to make a <hi>good Physician;</hi> especially the <hi>Vulgar</hi> of the <hi>Respective Parties</hi> they are of.</p>
                  <p>The third <hi>Sort</hi> are, These interested in some great <hi>Families,</hi> as having been <hi>Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mesticks, &amp;c.</hi> Or otherwise concerned there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, and who thereby come to <hi>Reputation</hi> Great Persons being called <hi>Gods,</hi> no wonde<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> they aim at <hi>Creation,</hi> and the making <hi>M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="3 letters">
                           <desc>•••</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi> out of <hi>Nothing▪</hi> and in no <hi>Faculty</hi> such a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <hi>Exploit</hi> as this seems so easie, as in <hi>Physick</hi> There is also a fourth <hi>sort,</hi> that by a <hi>Gent<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meen</hi> screw themselves into Peoples <hi>Liking</hi> and <hi>Familiarity.</hi> or by a <hi>Facetious Conversa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> by making Sports, and by telling little <hi>quirck knacks</hi> and <hi>Mimical-Stories,</hi> to divert whereby they gain the Opinion of being thought Witty and fine Men, while there is nothing <hi>solid</hi> or <hi>profitable</hi> to be found in their <hi>Conversation;</hi> but since the most part are more delighted with shows or with <hi>vain and fro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>thy Discourse,</hi> than with what is <hi>serious, solid,</hi> and <hi>useful,</hi> and that <hi>Fame</hi> Buoyes up <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ghter things, letting the <hi>weightier</hi> fall to
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:174794:62"/>the <hi>bottom,</hi> no wonder such be easily carri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed on the <hi>Wings</hi> of the Wind.</p>
                  <p>But to insist too much upon such things, may be rather constructed an <hi>Invective</hi> against the <hi>Elder,</hi> than an Admonition to younger <hi>Physicians.</hi> Certain yet it is, the profession must be fallen into a strange <hi>Declination</hi> and <hi>Deliquium,</hi> which makes it so much <hi>Depretiated,</hi> and <hi>Vilipended.</hi> that not only weak <hi>Physicians,</hi> but any ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther He or She, without Exception, come to be Trusted in the most <hi>Intricat</hi> and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portant concern of our <hi>Lives</hi> and <hi>Health,</hi> and that with, or before the most <hi>Accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plished Physician,</hi> yea, and without any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Qualification, but an impudent pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ending to understand the thing which is impossible for them to Comprehend. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as there is no thinking person, that makes a due Reflection upon the <hi>Intricary, difficulty</hi> and <hi>Danger,</hi> attending <hi>Medicinal Practice,</hi> that will think it so easy a thing, to have true <hi>Experience</hi> therein, tho every on Braggs of their <hi>Experience. Experience</hi> being a Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culty or <hi>Power</hi> acquired by constant and serious <hi>Observation,</hi> whereby the <hi>Physician</hi> is able rightly to Father the given <hi>Pheno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mena,</hi> or Visible effects upon their propper,
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:174794:63"/>tho hidden Causes. And <hi>felix qui potuil rerum Cognoscere causas,</hi> the linke betwixt <hi>Cause</hi> and <hi>Effect,</hi> lyes often <hi>too deep</hi> for <hi>Vulgar</hi> Eyes to discover it. And Conse<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently there is no <hi>Judicious Person</hi> but must Confess, that there is none Capable of any competent degree of Skil, or true <hi>Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience</hi> in this <hi>Art,</hi> who is not endued with the most Extraordinary <hi>Enduements</hi> of <hi>Mind,</hi> a most <hi>Penetrating Wit,</hi> an enlar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged and most <hi>Comprehensive Genius,</hi> Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to <hi>Reach, View,</hi> &amp; Ponder the State and Concurrence of all Circumstances of things and their <hi>Productive Capacities,</hi> relating to <hi>Experience</hi> in <hi>Practice,</hi> a ready <hi>Wite</hi> to <hi>Canvasse,</hi> and <hi>Examine,</hi> and a <hi>Solid</hi> and <hi>Sure Wit,</hi> to make <hi>Happy-hits,</hi> and he that is <hi>Preg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant</hi> in <hi>Medicine,</hi> where ever he shal turn his <hi>Eyes,</hi> whatever <hi>Object</hi> he <hi>Surveys,</hi> or subject, he shall bend his Mind upon, by his <hi>Pregnancy</hi> of <hi>Spirit,</hi> he will be Capable of making therein the like clear <hi>Discoveries</hi> and <hi>Just Hits. Solid</hi> and <hi>Sound Reasoning,</hi> makes <hi>Solid</hi> and <hi>Sound Acting;</hi> Those that <hi>Clin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi> and <hi>Quible,</hi> that <hi>Wrangle</hi> and <hi>Cavil</hi> in the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <hi>Reasonings,</hi> as all Weak-headed People do, are apt to do so in <hi>Action</hi> and <hi>Practice,</hi>
                     <pb n="31" facs="tcp:174794:63"/>about whatever Subject they medle. A great <hi>General, Politician</hi> or <hi>Lawyer</hi> would upon Application that way make a <hi>Good Physician</hi> and <hi>vice versa,</hi> a <hi>Qualified Physician,</hi> had he followed any of these <hi>Studys,</hi> would have been <hi>Exquisite</hi> therein; And as we may give the <hi>preheminence</hi> for <hi>difficulty</hi> and <hi>Intricacy</hi> to <hi>Physick,</hi> beyond all other <hi>Studys,</hi> so it is clear that <hi>Physick</hi> may be allowed to need the greatest <hi>Pregnancy</hi> of <hi>Wit</hi> and <hi>Judgment</hi> of any other Studys, and where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever the Young <hi>Physician</hi> sees not these in the <hi>Physician</hi> he followes; It is in vain for him to expect their Real <hi>Accomplishment, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>rue Skil,</hi> or <hi>Experience.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The Physician not only being a Mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>tor of the secret works, and of the hid in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>igues of Nature, but is also put upon the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ck and hard task of Governing and Dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>plinating Peoples <hi>Humours, prejudices,</hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nd <hi>Caprices,</hi> and has often more diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culty to graple with these, than with the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>iseases of the body, yea not only the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ents, but the Friends and By-standers by <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>eir <hi>mistakes</hi> and <hi>prejudices</hi> must give him <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>edless Work and trouble; But in this art of the Employment, the best <hi>Physician</hi>
                     <pb n="32" facs="tcp:174794:64"/>is oft outdone by the <hi>Weakest,</hi> who is more successfull herein, than the ablest, <hi>Quia A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quila non captat Muscas, the Eagle never catch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth Gnats,</hi> he that is taken up with, and most Conversant in, the <hi>Difficultys</hi> and <hi>Misterys</hi> of that <hi>Art,</hi> and has his mind in <hi>sublime,</hi> to him, it is tedious to stoop to the Servile Trivial and mean work of crouching to e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very <hi>Caprice</hi> and <hi>lying</hi> at <hi>Catch</hi> upon Peoples <hi>Humors,</hi> or <hi>waiting</hi> and <hi>Watching</hi> the Tides and turns thereof; And this Studying and <hi>Serving</hi> Peoples <hi>Humours,</hi> has to the <hi>Scandal</hi> of the <hi>Profession,</hi> made some <hi>Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sicians</hi> forego the <hi>Study</hi> of <hi>Nature,</hi> and take themselves to the <hi>Study</hi> and <hi>Exercise</hi> of <hi>Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litick complaisance,</hi> and <hi>Sycophantish Humour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> Persons: not finding the true study and practise of <hi>Physick, able</hi> to recommend them, and so instead of following <hi>Medicina<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> Prudence,</hi> to treat <hi>Diseases</hi> with due <hi>Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumspection, Caution</hi> and <hi>Art,</hi> they follow a kind of <hi>Bastard prudence,</hi> or rather <hi>Arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice</hi> and <hi>Cunning,</hi> to <hi>Cajole</hi> the <hi>Humours,</hi> and <hi>strike</hi> in with the <hi>Fansies</hi> and <hi>Whimzies</hi> o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <hi>Weak</hi> persons, and <hi>Young Physicians</hi> would be admonished that they follow not the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample of such.</p>
                  <pb n="33" facs="tcp:174794:64"/>
                  <p>Thus as <hi>Vulgar opinion Error</hi> and <hi>mistake</hi> has given occasion to the <hi>Deradence</hi> and <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cay</hi> of <hi>Medicine:</hi> So these <hi>vices</hi> ought not to be obtruded on the <hi>Art</hi> of <hi>Physick,</hi> being thus brought thereinto, Neither let the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>certointy or <hi>Conjecturalness</hi> thereof, be ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jected, since it is thus also made a great deal more so: than otherwise it would have been, Neither are the <hi>Differences</hi> and <hi>Dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>agreement</hi> among <hi>Physitians</hi> to the Dispar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>agement of true <hi>Medicine,</hi> seeing vulgar er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> has given too much <hi>occasion</hi> for these also.</p>
                  <p>Tho <hi>Physick</hi> of its own nature has no more <hi>Uncertainly</hi> or <hi>Conjerturalnes</hi> than these other noble and usefull <hi>Proffessions</hi> of <hi>War, Law, Politicks, Navigation:</hi> in all which the event can be no more predicted or ascert<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ained than in <hi>Physick,</hi> and all that the <hi>Artist</hi> is Accomptable for, being the <hi>Rational</hi> and <hi>Prudent conduct,</hi> that nothing be <hi>Overdone</hi> or <hi>Undone,</hi> that was Possible to have been done; or that <hi>Art</hi> and <hi>Skil</hi> could suggest, nevertheless through the many Diversions &amp; discouragments <hi>Physitians</hi> ly under, from <hi>Vulgar Prejudice Errors</hi> and <hi>Mistaks,</hi> the practiss thereof is made a great deal more
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:174794:65"/>both <hi>Uncertain</hi> and <hi>Unsuccessful</hi> then other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise it would be. And for the <hi>Debates</hi> and <hi>Differences</hi> among <hi>Physitians,</hi> when they break the bonds of <hi>Charity</hi> and <hi>Humanity,</hi> they are only the faults of Men not of the <hi>Art.</hi> but when they are only in opinion, they are no more than whats incident to all other <hi>Professions,</hi> that are versant about particular Events, and pertinent debaits are a token of great industry and of a laudable Emulati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. And when Means <hi>Wits</hi> are all of one <hi>Size,</hi> their <hi>Penetration</hi> and <hi>Comprehension</hi> of the same <hi>Reach,</hi> and their <hi>Judgment</hi> of the same <hi>vigour,</hi> then may we expect their <hi>Opinions</hi> shall <hi>Jump;</hi> And I doubt if the 15 <hi>Lords</hi> of <hi>Session</hi> are always <hi>Unanimous</hi> in there <hi>Votes</hi> &amp; <hi>Decisions</hi> or if the <hi>Councel</hi> of <hi>state,</hi> or a <hi>Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil</hi> of <hi>War</hi> are all of one Mind, &amp; yet no bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy takes occasion from that to disparage there procedure.</p>
                  <p>And for the most part, these <hi>Dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferences</hi> and <hi>Debates</hi> among <hi>Physitians,</hi> proceed from the <hi>Pride, Self-conceit</hi> and <hi>Envy</hi> of some <hi>Physitians, whom Vulgar Opinion</hi> has mounted upon <hi>a Higher pinacle</hi> of <hi>fame.</hi> and <hi>Reputation,</hi> than their true <hi>worth</hi> and <hi>Merit,</hi> can <hi>Maintain</hi> and <hi>Suport,</hi> and whose
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:174794:65"/>
                     <hi>Real Weaknes</hi> &amp; <hi>Emptynes chaffes</hi> &amp; <hi>rages</hi> to see any worthy thing done in <hi>Physick</hi> but in dependance upon them <hi>fearing</hi> they may be <hi>overtoped</hi> by others whom their <hi>Eminence</hi> used to look down upon, whereas the <hi>Able Candid</hi> and <hi>Honest Physician,</hi> will soon <hi>dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern</hi> and <hi>Cordialy welcome</hi> what is worthy in <hi>Medicine,</hi> from whomsoever it chanceth to come, but that which he thinks <hi>Futile</hi> &amp; <hi>Trivial</hi> will nothing move him, nor will he ever make it the Ball of <hi>Contention,</hi> as some have most unmercifully done, by my sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere, tho weak <hi>Endeavours</hi> for the Advance<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of <hi>Medicine.</hi> But Thanks be to GOD, who favouring my honest purposes, has helped me to weather out so many storms <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>aised against me, for my plain Dealing a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout some <hi>Dismal Sinister</hi> and <hi>Self-seeking Designs,</hi> and some dangerous <hi>Vulgar Errors Prejudices</hi> and <hi>Caprices,</hi> such being of mis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chievous Consequence in <hi>Medicine,</hi> more <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>han in any other <hi>Profession,</hi> as they are in <hi>Publick Societies,</hi> and <hi>Governments</hi> more <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>han in <hi>private Cases.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And tho the evil <hi>Spirit</hi> that reged against <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e, be not yet quite subdued and <hi>Conquer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>d,</hi> yet I hope the Edge thereof is conside<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rably
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:174794:66"/>blunted; Providence having brought about some considerable things to disco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver my Innocency, and the Folly and Wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedness of these Secret Works, hatched so much in the dark to controul my Endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours, that they can now scarce find a <hi>Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther</hi> to own them, every one denying their Accession to the Lybels printed on the Subject, and shifting them from one to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other, except one poor <hi>Creature,</hi> who, call<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing himself a <hi>Stripling</hi> aged 27 <hi>Summers</hi> did most unhappily put his Name to his <hi>Elaborat</hi> six days <hi>Work:</hi> But this <hi>Stirpling</hi> reckoning his Age by the <hi>Summers,</hi> as the <hi>Horses</hi> Age uses to be reckoned by the <hi>Grass,</hi> must needs be a Kin to that <hi>Animal,</hi> and it is no wonder, than if a <hi>Young Colt</hi> has been more <hi>fool-hardy</hi> than the Rest.</p>
                  <p>Whoever shall narrowly view how things often go in the World, may be in a Hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror to think that in many Cases there is no Convincing Men, that they are in the wrong Way, without the most lament<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able and woful Experiences, &amp; that so many <hi>Deaths,</hi> so much <hi>Destruction</hi> and irreparable <hi>Ruine,</hi> is sometimes needfull to open Mens Eyes, and the dearest bought <hi>Experience</hi>
                     <pb n="37" facs="tcp:174794:66"/>to cure their <hi>Blindness,</hi> and that over the Belly of Somes Zealous and constant <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavours,</hi> to convince them of their <hi>Mistakes</hi> and <hi>Errors,</hi> as may be eminently seen in this Case, and I fear it be not the only Case.</p>
                  <p>He that takes upon him to be an <hi>Author,</hi> because he takes on him the Office of a <hi>Preacher</hi> to the World, according to the O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion of some, he ought to have these 3 <hi>Qualifications. First▪</hi> The <hi>Courage</hi> of a Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dier, to <hi>encounter</hi> and <hi>combate Ignorance, Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors,</hi> and <hi>Caprices,</hi> these <hi>obstinat</hi> Enemies of all <hi>Vertue, Justice</hi> and <hi>Truth.</hi> The <hi>2d.</hi> The <hi>Sense</hi> and <hi>Solidity</hi> of a <hi>Statesman,</hi> that he cumber not the World with any thing <hi>Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vial</hi> or <hi>unworthy.</hi> The <hi>3d.</hi> The <hi>Sincerity</hi> and <hi>Integrity</hi> of a <hi>Dying Man,</hi> that he im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose nothing false, or <hi>sophisticate</hi> in point of <hi>Fact</hi> or <hi>Reasoning.</hi> And how my Perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mances in this, and my former <hi>Essays,</hi> have answered these <hi>Qualifications;</hi> I must submit to my Readers, who seing they are not all alike capable, to the weakest sort of them I crave Liberry to propose these following Considerations, before they give their Sentence; as first, That they would be
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:174794:67"/>pleased to consider the strange <hi>Schock</hi> of <hi>Violent</hi> and <hi>Universal Opposition,</hi> I have had and the small assistance of any Man, as <hi>I</hi> did in my first Book, predict and expect. Secondly, What <hi>estimate</hi> and <hi>value</hi> may be put upon my Subject, which is a more effectual way of treating these <hi>Formidable Fevers,</hi> which are a Terror to many <hi>Persons</hi> and <hi>Families,</hi> and which now seems to have to Suffrage of the most decerning part of <hi>Physicians</hi> here.</p>
                  <p>But for the third Qualification, since it's not so obvious to Men, I Bless GOD I have a clear Conscience that I never told any thing but Truth in the Commendation, &amp; in<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>stances of the <hi>Success</hi> of this way of treating <hi>Fevers,</hi> and even from my very <hi>Heart</hi> and <hi>Soul,</hi> and that by innumerable and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peated <hi>Instances,</hi> and Experiences these 12 Years confirmed.</p>
                  <p>Now in the next place, it is but Reason<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able I should whisper my Enemies in the Ear, how many of these <hi>Qualifications</hi> they can make good to Vindicate their Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comming <hi>Authors,</hi> for I fear if their Read<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers lay aside the <hi>Cavilling</hi> and <hi>quibling</hi> the <hi>Bitter</hi> and <hi>Malitious Invectives</hi> and
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:174794:67"/>
                     <hi>Slanders,</hi> there will be litle left in their Books, either <hi>Good</hi> or <hi>ill.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>I shall only give the Reader one of their mildest <hi>Bourds,</hi> because they thought a <hi>Master-peice</hi> of <hi>Wit,</hi> and it is in the end of their Dialogue thus, that they would not allow me to come into the Rank of <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors,</hi> with the <hi>Infamous Tartaretus,</hi> who wrote <hi>de modo Cacandi,</hi> because, say they, with a Perverted Authority, <hi>Mihi ex pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jori luto finxit proecordia Titan,</hi> but whoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver will take the Pains, to view the whole of the Treatment in this matter will, surely see it was not the <hi>Itch</hi> of <hi>Writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> took these Men, it has been the <hi>Scab,</hi> the <hi>Leprosie,</hi> and <hi>Botch</hi> of <hi>Writing,</hi> or rather <hi>Scribling</hi> and <hi>Blotting</hi> that seized them; Such <hi>Blunders</hi> against any Man, tho only Verbal are <hi>Scandalous</hi> enough. But if for well doing they are <hi>Divellish,</hi> as being not only the brandeing the Innocent but Truth and Righteousness it self. But Committed to <hi>Print,</hi> they fix E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternally and indelibly the <hi>Blackest stain</hi> on the <hi>Authors,</hi> and <hi>Abettors,</hi> both in the Eyes of GOD and Man, unless it be wip'd <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ff, as I pray it may be, by their sincere and
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:174794:68"/>hearty Repentance. But let them know thete is no true Repentance without a <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portionable Amendement,</hi> and endeavour of <hi>Reparation</hi> of the <hi>Damnage</hi> they have done the thing, not me, I mean.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Non tollitur peccatum nisi restituatur ablatum.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               </div>
            </body>
            <back>
               <div type="by_the_same_author">
                  <head>Advertisement.</head>
                  <p>THE Vindicatory <hi>Schedule</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the new cure of Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>De Febribus continuis Tentamen The<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oretica-Practicum.</hi> &amp;e. both shewing the Nature and Cure of <hi>Fevers,</hi> by the Author of this Epilogue; Sold by <hi>John Vallance</hi> Book-selle<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> near the Cross, <hi>Edinburgh.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:174794:68"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:174794:69"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:174794:69"/>
               </div>
            </back>
         </text>
      </group>
   </text>
</TEI>